<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-02-28T09:16:19+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/index.xml</id><title type="html">page_title</title><subtitle>page_description</subtitle><author><name>mehr.wert Software und IT Beratung GmbH</name></author><entry><title type="html">Embodied carbon in IT - the hidden carbon footprint of our digital world</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embodied carbon in IT - the hidden carbon footprint of our digital world" /><published>2025-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1"><![CDATA[<p>In today’s digital world, much revolves around software, data, and networking. However, behind every digital application lies a physical infrastructure: data centers, servers, networking technology, and end devices. While the focus is often on energy efficiency and renewable power sources, a significant environmental impact remains overlooked – <em>Embodied Carbon</em>.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-embodied-carbon"><strong>What is Embodied Carbon?</strong></h2>

<p>The term <em>Embodied Carbon</em> refers to the total CO₂ emissions generated throughout the lifecycle of an IT product – from raw material extraction to production, transportation, and disposal. Unlike <em>Operational Carbon</em>, which accounts for emissions from energy consumption during use, <em>Embodied Carbon</em> often constitutes the larger share of environmental impact.</p>

<p>For example: <strong>Up to 98% of the total CO₂ emissions of a smartphone or laptop occur during manufacturing.</strong> Similarly, the production of a server, depending on its configuration, <strong>generates between 100 and 3,000 kilograms of CO₂ equivalents.</strong> The <strong>Embodied Carbon</strong> accounts for approximately <strong>75% of the total CO₂ emissions of a rack server.</strong> In comparison: <strong>A smartphone generates around 55 kilograms of CO₂ equivalents due to Embodied Carbon, while a laptop generates about 300 kilograms.</strong> <a href="https://globalelectronicscouncil.org/wp-content/uploads/GEC_Climate_Change_SOSR_DRAFT_For_Public_Comment_1APR2021.pdf">(Source)</a></p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/smart-phone_vs_rack-server-de.png" alt="Comparison of Embodied Carbon and Operational Carbon in IT hardware" />
<small>Source: <a href="https://globalelectronicscouncil.org/wp-content/uploads/GEC_Climate_Change_SOSR_DRAFT_For_Public_Comment_1APR2021.pdf">globalelectronicscouncil.org</a></small></p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/carbon-compairison-different-devices-de.png" alt="Comparison of Embodied Carbon and Operational Carbon in IT hardware" />
<small>Source: <a href="https://globalelectronicscouncil.org/wp-content/uploads/GEC_Climate_Change_SOSR_DRAFT_For_Public_Comment_1APR2021.pdf">globalelectronicscouncil.org</a></small></p>

<h2 id="why-is-embodied-carbon-so-relevant"><strong>Why is Embodied Carbon So Relevant?</strong></h2>

<p>The production of IT hardware is extremely resource- and energy-intensive. It requires the extraction and processing of rare materials such as cobalt, lithium, silicon, and gold. The environmental consequences are severe:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>High energy consumption</b>: The production of microprocessors and other high-tech components requires vast amounts of electricity, often sourced from fossil fuels.</li>
<li><b>Resource exploitation</b>: The extraction of rare metals leads to environmental destruction, water pollution, and social issues in mining regions.</li>
<li><b>Short life cycles</b>: Rapidly changing technology trends result in shorter device lifespans – often replaced despite still being functional.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="ways-to-reduce-embodied-carbon"><strong>Ways to Reduce Embodied Carbon</strong></h2>

<p>To mitigate the <em>Embodied Carbon</em> of IT hardware, several strategies are essential:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Extended device lifespan</b>: Repairs, upgrades, and prolonged usage of devices significantly improve their environmental balance.</li>
<li><b>Circular economy</b>: Companies should focus on reuse and recycling to recover raw materials and reduce the need for new production.</li>
<li><b>Sustainable manufacturing</b>: Manufacturers must develop lower-emission production processes and increase the use of recycled materials.</li>
<li><b>Conscious consumer behavior</b>: Users can contribute by making informed purchasing decisions and adopting sustainable IT strategies.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>

<p>While the IT industry has made great strides in reducing <em>Operational Carbon</em>, <em>Embodied Carbon</em> remains an often-overlooked factor. Businesses and consumers must recognize the full environmental impact and implement sustainable strategies to minimize CO₂ emissions throughout a product’s lifecycle.</p>

<p><strong>Sustainable IT does not begin when a device is powered on – it starts with its production.</strong></p>

<h2 id="outlook"><strong>Outlook</strong></h2>

<p>In the upcoming articles in this series, we will take a closer look at the environmental impact of hardware production and disposal. We will also look at the life cycle of data centers and analyze their environmental challenges and possible sustainable solutions.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina, Marcel</name></author><category term="de" /><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In today’s digital world, much revolves around software, data, and networking. However, behind every digital application lies a physical infrastructure: data centers, servers, networking technology, and end devices. While the focus is often on energy efficiency and renewable power sources, a significant environmental impact remains overlooked – Embodied Carbon.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green coding - sustainability in software development</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green coding - sustainability in software development" /><published>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding"><![CDATA[<p>At a time when the climate crisis and sustainability have become key issues, the IT industry and its energy consumption are also coming more into focus. The constant increase in energy requirements and the growing consumption of resources are presenting companies and developers with new challenges. In this context, green coding approaches are becoming increasingly relevant. It offers solutions to make software more efficient and thus make a direct contribution to reducing its ecological footprint.</p>

<h4 id="what-is-behind-green-coding"><strong>What is behind green coding?</strong></h4>
<p>Green coding is a comprehensive approach that optimizes not only the code itself, but also the entire software architecture. It takes into account the consumption of resources over the entire life cycle of the software in order to keep this as low as possible. Decisions such as the choice of algorithms, data structuring and the location of the data center play an important role. For example, the use of scalable system architectures can reduce energy consumption and ensure that software runs more efficiently on different hardware configurations. The selection of energy-efficient programming languages, such as Rust, also makes a significant contribution to reducing power consumption.</p>

<h4 id="benefits-for-companies-and-the-environment"><strong>Benefits for companies and the environment</strong></h4>
<p>Companies that implement green coding practices benefit from numerous advantages. These not only have a positive impact on the environment, but also increase the company’s competitiveness.By reducing energy consumption, operating costs are reduced and the service life of the hardware can also be extended. Furthermore, companies that invest in sustainable software development make an active contribution to their ESG criteria (Environmental, Social, Governance), which are increasingly expected by investors and the public. With the introduction of the Corporate Sustainability Reporting Directive (CSRD) in the EU, many companies are now obliged to report regularly on their sustainability practices.The integration of green coding not only supports the fulfillment of these reporting obligations, but also strengthens the corporate image in terms of environmental responsibility.</p>

<h4 id="approaches-for-companies"><strong>Approaches for companies</strong></h4>
<p>One promising option for companies to implement green coding is the use of cloud infrastructures and virtualization technologies. These not only offer the flexibility to scale resources as required, but also the opportunity to use them more efficiently. If companies choose cloud service providers that operate their data centers with renewable energy, they can further reduce their CO2 emissions. At the same time, it is important to continuously monitor energy consumption in order to identify and exploit potential savings at an early stage. After all, we can only improve what we measure. As energy consumption cannot always be measured directly, companies should use proxy values to estimate consumption in such cases.</p>

<h4 id="challenges-and-opportunities"><strong>Challenges and opportunities</strong></h4>
<p>Rebound effects often occur when savings in one area are offset by increased use in another area. For example, more efficient software could lead to it being used more frequently, which would result in higher energy consumption overall. To prevent such effects, it is crucial to understand sustainability as a long-term strategy. By continuously improving the software and taking environmental effects into account throughout the entire development phase, a permanent reduction in resource consumption can be achieved.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding-as-a-corporate-strategy"><strong>Green coding as a corporate strategy</strong></h4>
<p>Green coding is not only a means of reducing CO2 emissions, but also a driver of innovation. Companies that focus on sustainable software development are positioning themselves as pioneers in the field of green technologies - one of the fastest growing markets in Germany. This not only gives them a competitive advantage, but also makes an important contribution to the digital transformation by developing technologies that meet the requirements of a sustainable future.</p>

<p>However, sustainable software development involves more than just efficient code or innovative technologies. It also requires a holistic view of the energy and resource requirements of digital services.</p>

<h4 id="the-energy-requirements-of-digital-services"><strong>The energy requirements of digital services</strong></h4>
<p>The high energy consumption of digital services makes it urgently necessary to evaluate them not only in terms of their functionality, but also with regard to their ecological footprint. The choice of data center in which applications are operated has a major influence on energy efficiency. Data centers that are powered by renewable energy or are located in regions where energy requirements are predominantly covered by sustainable sources can significantly reduce CO2 emissions. In addition, waste heat from data centers can be reused, for example through district heating or to heat greenhouses. Technologies such as edge computing also help to bring computing power closer to the end user and minimize the energy required for data transfer.</p>

<p>However, energy efficiency does not only depend on the infrastructure. The way in which software is developed and designed also plays a decisive role.</p>

<h4 id="more-than-just-optimized-code-the-holistic-approach"><strong>More than just optimized code: The holistic approach</strong></h4>
<p>The architecture of software has a significant influence on its long-term energy efficiency. A modular and scalable architecture makes it possible to flexibly adapt the software to different requirements without wasting unnecessary resources. Another important factor is the use of microservices, which enable applications to be scaled according to demand, thus avoiding unnecessary loads and improving energy efficiency. This approach is particularly advantageous in cloud environments, where resources can be flexibly allocated and released again, leading to a significant reduction in energy consumption.</p>

<p>Modern development practices and close collaboration within the teams are essential for the successful implementation of these approaches.</p>

<h4 id="devops-as-the-key-to-sustainable-software"><strong>DevOps as the key to sustainable software</strong></h4>
<p>DevOps principles promote close collaboration between the development department and IT operations and make it possible to integrate sustainability goals throughout the software lifecycle. Automated testing, continuous delivery and monitoring tools are not only valuable instruments for improving software quality, but also for optimizing resource consumption. By identifying inefficient code passages at an early stage and continuously adapting them to the latest, energy-efficient best practices, more sustainable development is promoted. DevOps also makes it possible to regularly review the energy consumption of software so that developers can take targeted measures to reduce CO2 emissions.</p>

<p>An equally important aspect of sustainable software development is the targeted selection of tools and technologies used in the development process - including the programming language.</p>

<h4 id="programming-language-as-an-influencing-factor"><strong>Programming language as an influencing factor</strong></h4>

<p>The choice of programming language has a significant impact on resource consumption. While interpreted languages such as Python and Ruby are widely used due to their flexibility and ease of use, they often perform worse in terms of efficiency and speed than compiled languages such as Rust or C++. These programming languages work closer to the hardware and offer better memory management and lower energy consumption. A conscious choice of programming language can therefore significantly reduce the ecological footprint of an application and increase performance at the same time.</p>

<p>However, the implementation of green coding goes beyond the choice of programming language. It requires a holistic approach and the implementation of sustainable practices, which are now also being successfully applied by leading companies.</p>

<h4 id="examples-from-practice"><strong>Examples from practice</strong></h4>
<p>Companies such as Google, Apple and Microsoft are not only pioneers in the use of green technologies, but also in the integration of green coding as an integral part of their software development. Google uses AI algorithms to optimize energy consumption in its data centers, Apple is pursuing carbon-neutral production and Microsoft has set itself the goal of becoming CO2-negative by 2030. These best practices serve as role models for other companies that are also striving for more sustainable software development. It is becoming clear that green coding is not only seen as an ethical responsibility, but also as an economic necessity to remain competitive and meet the demands of an increasingly environmentally conscious society.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding-in-germany"><strong>Green Coding in Germany</strong></h4>
<p>In Germany, more and more companies and start-ups are recognizing the importance of green coding and integrating sustainable development practices into their business models. Politicians are also promoting sustainable software development, for example through initiatives such as the ‘Blue Angel’, which tests software products in terms of their energy consumption and resource efficiency. Nevertheless, there is still a lot of potential for improvement, particularly in the area of certifying sustainable software products and establishing uniform standards. Although the path to more sustainable software development is not yet fully paved, current developments show that a change in awareness is underway.</p>

<h4 id="shaping-a-sustainable-digital-future"><strong>Shaping a sustainable digital future</strong></h4>
<p>The responsibility for a sustainable digital future lies not only with developers and companies, but also with consumers, regulatory authorities and society as a whole. Every player in the digital ecosystem must be involved in the transformation process to ensure the sustainable and resource-efficient use of software. Companies that integrate green coding into their processes not only set an example of ecological responsibility, but also prove that economic success and environmental awareness can go hand in hand. At the same time, it is necessary for politicians to create clear framework conditions that pave the way for a sustainable digital transformation, for example through legal requirements for energy efficiency and the promotion of green innovations.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding-as-a-corporate-strategy-1"><strong>Green coding as a corporate strategy</strong></h4>
<p>The integration of green coding into the corporate strategy goes beyond the mere implementation of efficient practices - it is a long-term process that must be deeply rooted in the corporate culture. Companies that successfully implement green coding ensure that sustainability is not just a one-off project, but an ongoing, dynamic challenge. Through close collaboration between development teams, sustainability departments and executives, the potential of green coding is fully exploited to develop sustainable software solutions that minimize the environmental footprint while promoting economic growth.</p>

<h4 id="outlook---the-path-to-a-sustainable-digital-future"><strong>Outlook - The path to a sustainable digital future</strong></h4>
<p>The path to a sustainable digital future requires a comprehensive change in the way software is developed, deployed and used. Green coding plays a key role in this, but in order to achieve the desired climate targets, all players - from software developers to companies and users - must take responsibility. Sustainability in software development is no longer just an option, but a necessity to ensure a future worth living for generations to come. Today’s measures, even if they may seem small, form the basis for a sustainable digital future that is not only technologically advanced but also ecologically responsible.</p>

<p>We want to be an active part of this green digital future and have already made a contribution to bringing sustainable software development into focus. Through our involvement in various publications, we are committed to further raising awareness of green coding and promoting best practices in the industry. Those interested can take a look at the article on Dev Insider, which deals with the importance of green coding and sustainable software development (read here: <a href="https://www.dev-insider.de/green-coding-nachhaltige-softwareentwicklung-a-a6b6dd926903508b9302fe1b2c7f5b0d/" target="_blank">Culturally anchoring green coding in the company</a>). We also contributed to a guideline published by the German Economic Institute, which examines the potential of green coding in the context of digital transformation and provides important impetus for companies and political decision-makers (read more here: &lt;a href=“https://www.wirtschaft-digital-bw.de/fileadmin/media/Dokumente/Studien/20240607_IW4Null_GreenCoding.pdf” target=“_blank”&gt;Green Coding - Increasing efficiency through the intelligent use of software&lt;/a&gt;).</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina, Marcel</name></author><category term="de" /><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At a time when the climate crisis and sustainability have become key issues, the IT industry and its energy consumption are also coming more into focus. The constant increase in energy requirements and the growing consumption of resources are presenting companies and developers with new challenges. In this context, green coding approaches are becoming increasingly relevant. It offers solutions to make software more efficient and thus make a direct contribution to reducing its ecological footprint.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green software, green future - sustainability in the digital age</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-software" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green software, green future - sustainability in the digital age" /><published>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-software</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-software"><![CDATA[<p>Whether uploading a photo, streaming a movie or using a cloud app - the internet makes our everyday lives more convenient. But this convenience comes at a price: enormous energy consumption that often remains invisible. Every digital action - from sending an email to using data-intensive AI services - adds up to a global energy consumption comparable to that of the global aviation industry.</p>

<p>At a time when the climate crisis and sustainability are key issues, the IT industry is also coming under the spotlight. How can we make the digital world more efficient and environmentally friendly? And what role does green coding play in this?</p>

<h4 id="the-internets-hunger-for-energy">The internet’s hunger for energy</h4>
<p>At first glance, the internet appears to be an invisible global network, but behind it lies an impressive physical infrastructure. Whether writing emails, streaming videos or making search queries - everything we do online passes through global networks and ultimately ends up in data centers. These “hubs” of the internet are indispensable for the digital world, but they consume enormous amounts of energy.</p>

<p>According to the International Energy Agency (IEA), data centers will consume around 200 terawatt hours of electricity worldwide in 2022, which corresponds to just under 1% of global electricity consumption. By comparison, this is almost equivalent to the annual energy requirements of countries such as Thailand. This consumption will continue to rise as global data traffic increases by around 20-30% annually.</p>

<p>Data-intensive applications such as streaming services or AI applications in particular are contributing massively to this. Here are a few examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>Streaming a two-hour 4K movie requires around 15 kWh of energy - enough to keep a light bulb on for 150 hours.</li>
<li>Uploading a 10 MB photo consumes around 0.2 kWh - equivalent to the power consumption of an LED lamp for around 12 hours.</li>
<li>One hour of using a cloud service to process large files can consume up to 0.5 kWh, which corresponds to the power consumption of an average lamp for approx. 25 hours.</li></ul>

<h4 id="the-connection-between-it-and-power-consumption">The connection between IT and power consumption</h4>
<p>The increasing energy requirements of IT infrastructure have far-reaching effects on global electricity consumption and therefore on our environment. High energy consumption leads to increased CO₂ emissions, especially in regions that generate most of their electricity from fossil fuels.</p>

<p>Global electricity consumption amounted to around 28,000 terawatt hours (TWh) in 2023. IT and digital technologies account for a significant proportion of this. It is particularly problematic that many data centers are still powered by coal, gas or oil-fired power plants, which leads to high CO₂ emissions. It is estimated that the IT industry is already responsible for 2-4% of global CO₂ emissions - a proportion that is comparable to the aviation industry and is continuing to rise.</p>

<p>The climate targets make the urgency clear: global greenhouse gas emissions are to be drastically reduced by 2050 in order to limit global warming to a maximum of 1.5 °C. However, in view of the growing energy consumption due to digital technologies and developments to date, this target no longer seems achievable. This makes it all the more important to systematically restructure the economy and the technology sector in particular in order to curb climate change as much as possible.</p>

<p>This is where green IT comes in: more efficient technologies, the switch to renewable energies and resource-saving approaches such as green coding are no longer visions of the future, but urgently needed solutions.</p>

<h4 id="resource-consumption-beyond-energy">Resource consumption beyond energy</h4>
<p>In addition to energy consumption, the consumption of resources in IT is also of crucial importance. The manufacture and disposal of devices such as servers, computers and mobile devices requires a large number of raw materials, including rare earths. These raw materials are only available in very limited quantities and their extraction and processing in particular entail considerable risks for the environment. The disposal of electronic waste is also a growing problem, as many devices are not recycled or reused. A sustainable IT industry must therefore not only reduce energy consumption, but also optimize the use of resources and extend the service life of devices.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding---code-neu-denken">Green Coding - Code neu denken</h4>
<p>Green Coding takes a holistic approach to minimizing the energy consumption of software and digital applications. The aim is to design digital products in such a way that they conserve resources while maximizing their functionality. Three principles play a decisive role here:</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Energy Efficiency:</b> Software should be optimized so that its operation consumes less energy. This means, for example, that computing operations are carried out more efficiently and resource-intensive processes are minimized.</li>
<li><b>Hardware Efficiency:</b> The software must work efficiently with the hardware in order to reduce energy consumption. This also includes optimizing software so that it harmonizes better with existing devices and infrastructures. The aim is to achieve the longest possible hardware life cycle.</li>
<li><b>Carbon Awareness:</b> Developers should be aware of the CO₂ emissions generated by the operation of software and its infrastructure. The aim is to design digital products and applications in such a way that they have a minimal carbon footprint.</li></ul>

<h4 id="shaping-a-sustainable-digital-future">Shaping a sustainable digital future</h4>
<p>The energy consumption of the internet and IT infrastructure is a significant factor in the global energy budget. Data centers contribute significantly to this consumption. However, it is possible to significantly reduce the impact through green IT and especially green coding. Here are a few examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Use of green energy:</b> Many data centers are increasingly turning to renewable energies to make their operations more climate-friendly. Switching to solar, wind or hydroelectric power can significantly reduce CO₂ emissions. Large companies such as Google and Microsoft have already started to run their data centers on 100% renewable energy and are even aiming to make their entire infrastructure CO₂-neutral.</li>
<li><b>Recycling of waste heat:</b> Some data centers use the waste heat generated to heat neighbouring buildings or even feed it into district heating networks. One example of this is the EcoDataCenter data center in Sweden, which uses its waste heat to supply a nearby residential area with energy. Such innovative approaches not only help to optimize energy consumption, but also contribute to reducing CO₂ emissions.</li></ul>

<p>The digital transformation offers many opportunities, but it also brings with it the responsibility to make our technologies as efficient and resource-saving as possible. Green coding is a crucial part of this responsibility, as it aims to operate the digital world with less energy and therefore fewer CO₂ emissions. To this end, the companies that develop and operate these technologies must also be held accountable by ensuring that their infrastructure - from software to data centers - is as green and sustainable as possible.</p>

<p>Overall, as a society and as an industry, we need to recognize that the transition to more sustainable IT practices is not just an option, but an urgent obligation. It is up to us to shape the digital future in a way that promotes both technological progress and the protection of our planet.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="de" /><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Whether uploading a photo, streaming a movie or using a cloud app - the internet makes our everyday lives more convenient. But this convenience comes at a price: enormous energy consumption that often remains invisible. Every digital action - from sending an email to using data-intensive AI services - adds up to a global energy consumption comparable to that of the global aviation industry.]]></summary></entry></feed>