<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2026-01-30T08:27:29+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/index.xml</id><title type="html">page_title</title><subtitle>page_description</subtitle><author><name>mehr.wert Software und IT Beratung GmbH</name></author><entry><title type="html">n8n Reality Check - Productivity Gain or Programming with a User Interface?</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/n8n-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="n8n Reality Check - Productivity Gain or Programming with a User Interface?" /><published>2026-01-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2026-01-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/en/n8n-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/en/n8n-1"><![CDATA[<p>Automation Between Orchestration and Hidden Complexity.</p>

<p>Low-code workflow automation promises efficiency, speed, and less manual work. Tools like n8n embrace this promise—with a visual interface, numerous integrations, and the ability to quickly piece together processes. But how much actual added value do they still provide today? And where are the limits of such low-code approaches?</p>

<p>This article provides a critical assessment of n8n—technically, organizationally, and with a view to resource-efficient software development.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-n8nand-what-is-it-not">What is n8n—and what is it not?</h2>

<p>n8n is a platform for <strong>workflow automation</strong>. So-called <em>triggers</em> (e.g., webhooks or schedules) initiate <em>nodes</em> that perform actions: API calls, database queries, if/else logic, or data transformations. This creates workflows that move data between systems and automate processes.</p>

<p>Typical use cases include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A form is submitted → data lands in the CRM → a Slack message is sent</li>
  <li>An invoice arrives by email → information is extracted → accounting is updated</li>
</ul>

<p>It is important to classify n8n correctly: <strong>n8n is not a classic no-code tool</strong>. At the latest with expressions, custom nodes, and especially the <strong>code nodes</strong> where JavaScript or Python is executed, you are clearly in the <strong>low-code realm</strong>. The real value lies not in “coding without code” but in the <strong>orchestration of logic, APIs, and processes</strong>. However, this also carries a risk: <strong>complex software is easily disguised as a simple flow</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="which-needs-does-n8n-address">Which needs does n8n address?</h2>

<p>n8n targets not so much clearly defined roles but certain <strong>motivations</strong> found in many teams:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Processes should be <strong>automated quickly</strong> without long development cycles</li>
  <li>Manual, error-prone work should be reduced</li>
  <li>Data and infrastructure should remain <strong>under own control</strong> (self-hosting)</li>
  <li>Solutions should work pragmatically—even with limited development resources</li>
</ul>

<p>From these needs arise typical contexts of use: tech-savvy engineering or platform teams, operations and DevOps areas with many SaaS tools, as well as SMEs and startups prioritizing speed over formal architecture.</p>

<p>The critical point: n8n appears externally as “no-code for everyone,” but in practice it requires users to have at least <strong>basic coding skills</strong>—enough to understand data structures, follow logic, and configure nodes meaningfully. Thus, n8n is mostly <strong>low-code for people who can handle complexity, debugging, and operations</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="what-n8n-does-well">What n8n does well</h2>

<p>To be fair, n8n brings clear strengths:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Rapid prototyping</strong> of integrations through many pre-built nodes</li>
  <li><strong>Self-hosting</strong> enables data sovereignty and flexible integration into existing stacks</li>
  <li><strong>Extensibility</strong> through custom nodes and code nodes</li>
  <li>Support for modern <strong>AI and agent workflows</strong>, which are currently in high demand</li>
</ul>

<p>For simple to medium integration scenarios, n8n can quickly create value—<strong>but this advantage is not exclusive</strong>: comparable results can often also be achieved with scripts, small services, or other low-code and integration tools.</p>

<p><strong>What low-code does not eliminate</strong></p>

<p>As with many low-code frameworks, the challenge lies less in getting started than in long-term operation. As complexity increases, visual workflows become confusing, changes harder to trace, and classic engineering practices like reviews, versioning, and testing more demanding. At the same time, integrations rarely fail at the surface but due to unstable APIs, rate limits, timeouts, or expiring tokens, requiring solid monitoring and error handling concepts. Self-hosting is no free lunch either: updates, backups, secrets and rights management, as well as security hardening, merely shift the effort. Code nodes in particular increase the attack surface and make clear role and permission concepts necessary. The initial speed advantage of low-code can thus be eaten up over time by rising maintenance, operational, and security costs.</p>

<h2 id="license-and-the-open-source-narrative">License and the open-source narrative</h2>

<p>Another aspect often overlooked in assessments of n8n is the <strong>license model</strong>. n8n is <em>source-available</em> under the Sustainable Use License: the source code is accessible, but usage is restricted—e.g., for resale or offering as a service.</p>

<p>This is fundamentally legitimate but often clashes with expectations. In a technical context, “open source” usually implies maximum freedom. For product providers, platform projects, or long-term strategic decisions, this license can therefore be a relevant criterion—or even a reason for exclusion.</p>

<h2 id="programming-with-a-user-interface">Programming with a user interface?</h2>

<p>One central question remains: <strong>Does n8n really help today to the extent it promises?</strong></p>

<p>Many workflows ultimately consist of logic, API calls, and data transformations that can also be implemented in classic code. n8n mainly takes over orchestration—not the domain-specific or technical complexity. Let’s remember: even with n8n, users need basic programming skills.</p>

<p>At the same time, modern <strong>AI-assisted coding tools</strong> significantly lower the entry barrier for classic implementations. Even with <strong>rudimentary programming skills</strong>, it is now possible to create functional applications and integrations quickly, e.g., with Copilot, ChatGPT, or Cursor.</p>

<p>Small services, scripts, or integrations can thus often be generated, tested, and adapted very quickly today—even without a visual workflow framework.</p>

<p>This raises the legitimate question whether n8n in many cases is rather <strong>programming with a user interface</strong>: the logic remains, only its representation changes.</p>

<h2 id="resource-efficiency-automation-is-not-automatically-cost-saving">Resource efficiency: automation is not automatically cost-saving</h2>

<p>Automation also consumes resources and thus causes direct and indirect costs. For example, if processes are implemented via polling instead of event-driven triggers, unnecessary computational load arises. High log and retention settings further increase storage needs and thus ongoing operational costs. Additionally, cluttered or outdated workflows often continue running permanently, consuming resources without delivering real added value.</p>

<p>From a <strong>resource efficiency</strong> perspective, automation should therefore be used deliberately and regularly reviewed. Event-driven designs, limited run frequencies, and conscious data and workflow lifecycle management help avoid unnecessary consumption—and thus <strong>significantly reduce ongoing costs</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-another-solution-for-a-known-problem">Conclusion: another solution for a known problem</h2>

<p>n8n is not a particularly strong or fundamentally new tool but primarily <strong>another solution for a known problem</strong>: the orchestration of integrations and automations. It does not replace engineering but shifts it into a visual interface. With the increasing power of AI-assisted coding tools, the question arises more and more whether the use of an additional low-code framework is still justified in every case.</p>

<p>n8n can work for clearly defined integrations—with clear ownership, monitoring, and security concepts. At the same time, one should be aware that it is ultimately <strong>programming with a user interface</strong>. Without corresponding discipline, it quickly becomes a hard-to-maintain collection of workflows that is hardly less complex than classic code.</p>

<p>The <strong>Profile Agent</strong> follows the same goal of <strong>increasing efficiency and automating recurring problems</strong>, but without visual workflows. Instead, it relies on structured logic and AI-assisted evaluation. You can read more about this approach in the article <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/profil-agent">Less Effort, Better Matches – The Profile Agent</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="Low-Code," /><category term="Workflow-Automation," /><category term="Softwareentwicklung," /><category term="Ressourceneffizienz," /><category term="Toolkritik," /><category term="KI-gestütztes-Coding," /><category term="Integration" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Automation Between Orchestration and Hidden Complexity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Less Effort, Better Matches – The Profile Agent</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/profil-agent" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Less Effort, Better Matches – The Profile Agent" /><published>2025-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/profil-agent</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/profil-agent"><![CDATA[<p>In many companies, it always starts the same way. A new project request comes in. Or a customer tender lands in the inbox. The topic is interesting, the requirements are manageable – but then the real challenge begins: <strong>Which employees are actually the right fit for this project?</strong></p>

<p>Who has the relevant experience? Who is currently available? And who might even be underutilized, yet would be a perfect match in terms of skills?</p>

<p>Instead of clear answers, a tedious search often begins. Profiles are gathered, Excel sheets opened, old Word documents copied and adapted. A lot of knowledge exists – but not where it is needed at that moment.</p>

<h2 id="the-real-problem-matching-takes-time">The Real Problem: Matching Takes Time</h2>

<p>The core issue is rarely a lack of expertise, but rather a lack of overview. Skills, project experience, and roles are spread across different systems or documented only superficially. At the same time, there is often no clear connection to employees’ <strong>utilization</strong>.</p>

<p>This leads to two typical situations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Responses to tenders are delayed, even though suitable profiles exist within the company.</li>
  <li>Employees with available capacity remain unnoticed, while other teams are overloaded.</li>
</ul>

<p>This is exactly where our <strong>Profile Agent</strong> comes into play.</p>

<h2 id="how-we-do-it-from-demand-to-the-right-profile">How We Do It: From Demand to the Right Profile</h2>

<p>The Profile Agent connects multiple sources of information into a single, coherent process. The starting point is either a project tender or an internal project demand. This input is automatically analyzed and structured.</p>

<p>At the same time, the system accesses existing employee data – such as project descriptions, roles, skills, and timelines. Optionally, <strong>utilization data</strong> can also be integrated. This makes it possible to identify employees who are a strong skills match <strong>and</strong> currently have available capacity.</p>

<p>The result is automatically generated short profiles that are precisely tailored to the specific context – for internal project planning as well as for external tenders.</p>

<h2 id="under-the-hood-structure-instead-of-guesswork">Under the Hood: Structure Instead of Guesswork</h2>

<p>From a technical perspective, the Profile Agent is based on a modular pipeline. A key component is <strong>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)</strong>.</p>

<p>Existing employee profiles are stored as a searchable knowledge base in a vector database. Relevant experience is retrieved in a targeted manner and combined with the requirements of the tender. A language model then ensures that the result is a coherent, natural-sounding short profile.</p>

<p>In addition, the Profile Agent calculates a <strong>match score</strong> that transparently shows how well a person fits a given request. This makes decisions more traceable – without removing humans from the process.</p>

<h2 id="adaptable-to-context-brand-and-language">Adaptable to Context, Brand, and Language</h2>

<p>Every organization communicates differently. That is why the generated profiles can be flexibly adapted – both to the company’s own corporate identity and to the <strong>corporate identity and tone of the customer</strong>. Language and writing style can also be adjusted as needed.</p>

<p>This results in profiles that not only fit from a technical perspective, but also integrate seamlessly into existing proposal and communication processes.</p>

<h2 id="real-value-in-everyday-work">Real Value in Everyday Work</h2>

<p>The value of the Profile Agent becomes clear in day-to-day operations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>faster responses to project and customer requests</li>
  <li>better use of existing skills and expertise</li>
  <li>greater transparency regarding skills and utilization</li>
  <li>consistent, high-quality profiles</li>
  <li>less manual coordination and less time spent searching</li>
</ul>

<p>In short: <strong>less effort, better matches.</strong></p>

<h2 id="no-talent-goes-unused">No Talent Goes Unused</h2>

<p>The Profile Agent follows a clear guiding principle: <strong>No talent goes unused.</strong> By structuring knowledge, making it accessible, and enabling context-aware use, it helps organizations match people to the right projects more effectively – efficiently, transparently, and sustainably.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="de" /><category term="posts" /><category term="#Künstliche" /><category term="Intelligenz," /><category term="#Wissensmanagement," /><category term="#Projektplanung," /><category term="#Ressourcenplanung" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In many companies, it always starts the same way. A new project request comes in. Or a customer tender lands in the inbox. The topic is interesting, the requirements are manageable – but then the real challenge begins: Which employees are actually the right fit for this project?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Knowledge management in everyday life – how Mehr.Wiki makes knowledge available on a long-term basis</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/mehrwiki" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Knowledge management in everyday life – how Mehr.Wiki makes knowledge available on a long-term basis" /><published>2025-12-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/mehrwiki</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/mehrwiki"><![CDATA[<p>Knowledge is one of the most valuable resources in companies—and at the same time one of the most transient. A colleague spends years acquiring in-depth expertise in projects, gathering experience, and developing best practices. But what happens when this knowledge only exists in presentations, local folders, or in her own head?</p>

<p>This is precisely where a central problem of modern knowledge work lies: skills are built up individually, but are often only available to the company as a whole to a limited extent. Project knowledge disappears into folder structures, insights are reworked multiple times, and valuable experience is lost as soon as teams change.</p>

<p>This is where <strong>Mehr.Wiki</strong> comes in: an internal knowledge database that captures and bundles precisely this knowledge and makes it accessible to everyone—in a sustainable, structured, and future-proof way.</p>

<h2 id="from-individual-knowledge-to-a-shared-resource">From individual knowledge to a shared resource</h2>

<p>Mehr.Wiki is the internal knowledge platform of Mehr.Wert GmbH. Technically, it is based on MediaWiki, the open-source software that also underpins Wikipedia. However, it is not so much the technology that is important as the idea behind it: knowledge acquired by individual employees in projects, research, or training should not remain isolated. In Mehr.Wiki, it is stored in such a way that others can quickly find, understand, and reuse it—regardless of who originally developed it.</p>

<h2 id="what-content-is-included-in-mehrwiki">What content is included in Mehr.Wiki?</h2>

<p>Mehr.Wiki contains content from a wide variety of technical contexts—from technical questions and methodological approaches to organizational topics. It is important to note that we deliberately avoid long, newly written “wiki articles” unless necessary. Instead, existing materials are entered in an <strong>accessible</strong> manner and briefly classified.</p>

<p>These include, for example, PDFs, presentations, Excel files, worksheets, and training materials. This creates a <strong>uniformly structured</strong> knowledge base from different sources that can be quickly used in everyday life.</p>

<h2 id="structure-instead-of-knowledge-silos">Structure instead of knowledge silos</h2>

<p>A central principle of Mehr.Wiki is a clear structure and taxonomy—and a deliberately streamlined approach to content. Instead of writing long texts or extensive editorial articles, existing media and materials are integrated simply, pragmatically, and as close as possible to their original form.</p>

<p>Documents, presentations, or working materials are stored in such a way that they can be found quickly and are clearly organized without being unnecessarily reworked. Categories and subcategories ensure that content is grouped thematically on overview pages.</p>

<p>The result: less maintenance, less duplication of work, and more transparency about what knowledge already exists in the company—and where it can be found.</p>

<p>In knowledge management in particular, it is clear time and again that <strong>less is often more</strong>. It is not the number of functions or perfectly crafted content that determines the success of a system, but its usability in everyday life. Low-threshold access, clear structures, and carefully selected, easily available tools lower the barrier to use – and ensure that knowledge is actually shared and developed further. This is precisely where the key to sustainable knowledge management lies.</p>

<h3 id="ai-supported-assistance-with-knowledge-processing">AI-supported assistance with knowledge processing</h3>

<p>To ensure that data entry remains fast, the tools used are embedded in a separate routine that serves as a <strong>content intake pipeline</strong>. This pipeline maps the entire process from reading and processing to storage in the wiki and makes it possible to collect and efficiently enter multiple documents.</p>

<p>We integrate <strong>commercially available API solutions</strong> for content processing: documents are analyzed automatically and provided with a <strong>short, compact summary</strong>. This mini-summary serves as an “introduction” so that colleagues can decide in seconds whether a document is relevant to them.</p>

<p>In this way, AI modules primarily support structure and orientation—not the rewriting of entire content. This keeps the effort low and makes knowledge management realistic in everyday work.</p>

<h2 id="robust-sustainable-and-expandable">Robust, sustainable, and expandable</h2>

<p>The most important sustainability factor of Mehr.Wiki is its <strong>suitability for everyday use</strong>: new content can be quickly added, updated, and sensibly categorized—without any major hurdles. It is precisely this low threshold that ensures that the wiki is actually used and continuously maintained, rather than becoming obsolete after a one-time “documentation phase.”</p>

<p>We support this technically through containerized operation. Existing content is retained during updates or restarts, and typical sources of error—such as special characters in file names or uploads that are too large—are reliably detected and communicated transparently. This ensures that Mehr.Wiki remains stable, expandable, and usable in the long term.</p>

<h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2>

<p>Mehr.Wiki is not a completed project, but an ongoing process. We are gradually developing the structure, workflows, and automation—always with the goal of making knowledge easy to share and permanently available within the company. The experience and principles gained in the process can also be transferred to other organizations and contexts where sustainable knowledge management plays a central role.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="sustainability," /><category term="knowledge," /><category term="wiki," /><category term="knowledge" /><category term="management," /><category term="green" /><category term="IT" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Knowledge is one of the most valuable resources in companies—and at the same time one of the most transient. A colleague spends years acquiring in-depth expertise in projects, gathering experience, and developing best practices. But what happens when this knowledge only exists in presentations, local folders, or in her own head?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Awareness and Responsibility – Why Sustainability Is More Than Just Technology</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-agile-guide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Awareness and Responsibility – Why Sustainability Is More Than Just Technology" /><published>2025-10-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-10-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-agile-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-agile-guide"><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago, I was asked to analyze the enterprise resource planning system of a major German supermarket chain. The system had evolved over decades — written in <em>Gupta</em>, a development environment that’s barely used today. One single file contained more than <strong>300,000 lines of source code</strong>. No modular structure. No documentation. No clear ownership.</p>

<p>No one really knew <strong>what</strong> the system was doing, <strong>why</strong> it worked the way it did — or <strong>what would break</strong> if even a minor change was made.</p>

<p>What followed wasn’t optimization — it was a complete rewrite. A multi-year project that demanded enormous resources: technically, economically, and humanly.</p>

<p>For me, this was a turning point. Because it showed me that sustainability in IT doesn’t start with energy measurements — it starts with <strong>awareness and responsibility</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="green-agile-starts-with-values">Green Agile Starts With Values</h2>

<p>In the <a href="https://greenagile.org">Green Agile Guide</a>, we often talk about sustainable practices: impact transparency, a green product backlog, ecological architecture decisions. But all of these methods are ineffective if they aren’t built on a <strong>foundation of values</strong>.</p>

<p>That’s why we’ve placed two guiding principles at the core of the guide:</p>

<h3 id="awareness">Awareness</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Understanding what software really <em>does</em> — technically, ecologically, socially</li>
  <li>Having the courage to name <strong>blind spots</strong> in teams and processes</li>
  <li>Seeing systems in context: Who uses them? What do they really need? What costs arise in 2, 5, or 10 years?</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Awareness means not just optimizing locally — but thinking globally.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="responsibility">Responsibility</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Making decisions even when they’re uncomfortable or more expensive short-term</li>
  <li>Naming technical debt — instead of ignoring it</li>
  <li>Taking long-term maintainability seriously</li>
  <li>Not delegating sustainability — but <strong>owning it as part of your role</strong></li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Responsibility means taking action — even when no one is watching.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-its-more-than-just-technology">Why It’s More Than Just Technology</h2>

<p>Many companies today invest in sustainability initiatives — from green coding to CO₂ compensation. That’s important. But without <strong>internalized values</strong>, it often remains symbolic.</p>

<p>Sustainability needs a culture in which people say:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“I understand what I’m doing — and I stand by the impact of my work.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s where Green Agile comes in. It’s not about new roles or checklists. It’s about bringing <strong>a new mindset</strong> into existing processes.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="what-can-you-do">What Can You Do?</h2>

<p>Here are some questions you can ask yourself — or your team:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Where are we missing <strong>transparency</strong> — technically or organizationally?</li>
  <li>Who is <strong>truly responsible</strong> — not just formally, but in reality?</li>
  <li>What decisions would we make differently if we thought <strong>more long-term</strong>?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next</h2>

<p>Over the next few weeks, I’ll share more elements of the Green Agile Guide in a short blog series — from practical techniques to role models and meaningful metrics. If you’re interested in applying the guide in your organization or contributing your thoughts, I’d love to hear from you.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Together, we can prove: <strong>Sustainable software doesn’t happen by accident. It’s built by people with awareness and responsibility.</strong></p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Marcel</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-agile," /><category term="#sustainability" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few years ago, I was asked to analyze the enterprise resource planning system of a major German supermarket chain. The system had evolved over decades — written in Gupta, a development environment that’s barely used today. One single file contained more than 300,000 lines of source code. No modular structure. No documentation. No clear ownership.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green Agile - Why We Need to Rethink Agility</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-agile" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Agile - Why We Need to Rethink Agility" /><published>2025-09-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-09-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-agile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-agile"><![CDATA[<p>When we talk about sustainability today, most people think of wind turbines, electric cars, or personal consumption. Hardly anyone thinks of software. Yet our digital systems hide a massive, invisible energy and resource footprint. Data centers consume more electricity than entire countries, and poorly optimized software forces hardware to be replaced far too quickly.</p>

<p>This topic has accompanied me for many years. As a <strong>software engineer</strong>, I’ve seen how small design decisions can make huge differences in energy consumption. Later, as an <strong>Agile Coach and RTE</strong>, I supported organizations in steering complex IT landscapes and teams. Again and again, I ran into the same gap: agility brings speed and adaptability – but the ecological dimension was left out.</p>

<p>This is exactly where <strong>Green Agile</strong> comes in.</p>

<h2 id="why-green-agile">Why Green Agile?</h2>

<p>Classical agile methods like Scrum, SAFe, or Kanban focus on delivery capability, customer value, and flexibility. All important values – but they fall short if we exclude long-term responsibility for environment and society.</p>

<p>Green Agile combines the <strong>principles of agility</strong> (transparency, inspection, adaptation) with the <strong>dimensions of sustainability</strong>:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Ecological</strong> – reducing energy consumption, extending hardware lifecycles, mindful use of resources</li>
  <li><strong>Economic</strong> – increasing efficiency, avoiding technical waste, building future-proof IT strategies</li>
  <li><strong>Social</strong> – healthy teams, fair collaboration, ethical awareness in product development</li>
</ul>

<p>Agility without sustainability is short-term. Sustainability without agility often remains theory. Only in combination can teams and organizations truly become future-proof.</p>

<h2 id="the-green-agile-guide">The Green Agile Guide</h2>

<p>To make this connection tangible, I created the <strong>Green Agile Guide</strong>. Inspired by the Scrum Guide, but deliberately extended. It’s not a new framework, not a collection of methods – but a <strong>mindset</strong> that provides orientation.</p>

<p>The Guide describes how teams can integrate ecological, economic, and social responsibility into their way of working, without sacrificing speed or flexibility. It’s about asking better questions:</p>
<ul>
  <li>What is the ecological footprint of our architecture?</li>
  <li>How do we measure sustainability alongside time-to-market and business value?</li>
  <li>How do we create structures that work not only for the next quarter but also for the next generation?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="outlook--and-my-stance">Outlook – and My Stance</h2>

<p>With my company <strong>mehr.wert</strong>, I support organizations as a <strong>Fractional CTO</strong>. My stance: technology and leadership should not only strive for efficiency and profit, but must also create <strong>more value for the world</strong>. Green Agile is one part of this vision.</p>

<p>I invite you to join the conversation, share your feedback, and help shape the Green Agile Guide. Because only together can we make IT not just faster, but also more sustainable.</p>

<p>👉 <a href="https://greenagile.org">Read the Green Agile Guide here</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Marcel</name></author><category term="de" /><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-agile," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When we talk about sustainability today, most people think of wind turbines, electric cars, or personal consumption. Hardly anyone thinks of software. Yet our digital systems hide a massive, invisible energy and resource footprint. Data centers consume more electricity than entire countries, and poorly optimized software forces hardware to be replaced far too quickly.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green Coding with AI – ChatGPT as a Tool for Sustainable Programming</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/KI-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Coding with AI – ChatGPT as a Tool for Sustainable Programming" /><published>2025-07-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/KI-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/KI-II"><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/KI">first part of our article series</a>, we explored the tension between <strong>Artificial Intelligence</strong> and <strong>sustainability</strong>: How can we ensure that AI is not just resource-intensive, but also contributes to solving ecological problems?</p>

<p>In this second part, we turn to the <strong>practical application</strong>: How can <strong>ChatGPT be used in everyday development</strong> to produce <strong>sustainable, energy-efficient code</strong>? We take a closer look at <strong>current research</strong>, analyze the <strong>strengths and weaknesses</strong> of LLMs, and show how these tools can already be tailored for <strong>Green Coding</strong> today—and how to put this <strong>potential to use</strong> right now.</p>

<p>Before diving into specific implementation methods in ChatGPT, we need to ask a fundamental question: <strong>Can a language model like ChatGPT even generate energy-efficient code—and if so, under what conditions?</strong> This potential needs to be confirmed before considering appropriate techniques and contexts for practical use. Let’s take a look at <strong>current research findings</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="can-chatgpt-actually-produce-energy-efficient-code">Can ChatGPT actually produce energy-efficient code?</h3>

<p>The answer is: <strong>Yes—under certain conditions</strong>. But not automatically. A key source here is the study “Generating Energy‑efficient Code with LLMs” (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10599">Tom Cappendijk et al., 2024</a>). In a controlled experiment, five large LLMs (including CodeLlama‑70b and DeepSeek‑Coder‑33b) were tasked with solving three different LeetCode problems. The prompts ranged from neutral instructions (“Solve this problem”) to specific phrasing such as “Give me an energy‑optimized solution…” or “Use library functions.”</p>

<p>The study concludes that <strong>energy savings through LLMs are generally possible</strong>—but not consistently. In some test scenarios, certain combinations of model, task type, and <strong>targeted prompting</strong> led to significant improvements in energy efficiency. For example, the use of <strong>efficient library functions</strong> or <strong>optimized loop structures</strong> resulted in savings of up to <strong>60%</strong>. At the same time, there was <strong>no prompt that consistently produced more efficient code</strong>; in some cases, the models even generated considerably less efficient code, especially for more complex tasks.</p>

<p>The decisive factor is <strong>prompting</strong>: Only when the prompt explicitly references energy efficiency or specific coding practices does the <strong>likelihood increase</strong> that the generated solution will be resource-conscious. Without such guidance, the energy efficiency of the output remains <strong>largely unpredictable</strong>.</p>

<p>The study shows: LLMs like ChatGPT <strong>can</strong> generate <strong>energy-efficient code</strong>—if <strong>guided accordingly</strong>. What matters are <strong>clear prompts</strong> and a meaningful <strong>context</strong>. Without them, the potential remains untapped.</p>

<h3 id="ai-powered-refactoring-what-the-research-tells-us">AI-powered Refactoring: What the Research Tells Us</h3>

<p>A major shortcoming of existing approaches is their focus on evaluating AI-generated code. They assess how energy-efficient a given output is—but offer no concrete method for automatically improving existing code. This is where a research team from Purdue University (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09241">Peng et al., 2024</a>) goes a step further: They developed a prototype for an automated <strong>refactoring system</strong>, in which <strong>two LLMs collaborate</strong> to systematically optimize existing code for energy efficiency.</p>

<p>Here’s how it works: A first model (e.g., GPT-4) analyzes the input code and suggests an <strong>optimized version</strong> designed to use fewer resources. A second model evaluates this suggestion—checking for <strong>functional correctness</strong> and measuring actual <strong>energy consumption</strong> using embedded telemetry and runtime data. Based on this feedback, the first model can then <strong>iteratively improve</strong> its suggestions.</p>

<p>The result: In about half of the test cases, <strong>energy consumption was significantly reduced</strong>—sometimes to less than half of the original level. Particularly notable: In several cases, the refactoring suggestions even outperformed what traditional <strong>compiler optimizations</strong> achieved.</p>

<p>This approach clearly highlights the <strong>potential of LLMs in sustainable software maintenance</strong>: Instead of merely generating efficient new code, they could also adapt existing code to meet modern <strong>efficiency standards</strong>—a promising outlook for future tools.</p>

<h3 id="green-coding-guidelines-how-to-train-chatgpt-with-context">Green Coding Guidelines: How to Train ChatGPT with Context</h3>

<p>To unlock the potential of LLMs like ChatGPT for everyday development, several proven strategies are already available. While research shows that LLMs do not inherently produce energy-efficient code, their output can be greatly improved through <strong>targeted prompting</strong> and <strong>contextual guidance</strong>.</p>

<p>If you want ChatGPT to consistently focus on energy efficiency in code generation, there are multiple ways to make that happen:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Persistent Custom Instructions</b><br />
With custom instructions (accessible via the settings menu in the ChatGPT app, available only for ChatGPT Plus/Enterprise), you can store permanent prompts that are automatically applied in every conversation. <br />
These instructions are used across contexts – regardless of the project or topic at hand.</li>

<li><b>Upload style guides or Markdown files</b><br />
GPT-4 supports file uploads. This allows you to provide your own guidelines directly as input – for example as `green_coding_guidelines.md` – and explicitly ask the model to follow them.</li>

<li><b>Create your own GPTs with system prompts</b><br />
Using the "Explore" feature, you can build specialized GPTs that consistently follow Green Coding goals – including fixed prompts and optional knowledge files.</li>

<li><b>Be clear and structured</b><br />
Rules should be positive, precise, and written in bullet points. Reinforcers such as “always” or “definitely” help the model prioritize effectively.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Good prompting is key</strong>—and sometimes a single sentence is enough to noticeably improve code suggestions. A prompt that has proven effective in practice reads:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Act as an experienced software developer. Review the following code for performance, maintainability, and energy efficiency. Provide specific, actionable suggestions for improvement in each of these areas.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This prompt is taken from a practical article by (<a href="https://ashexplained.com/how-to-improve-code-reviews-using-chatgpt/">Ash Explained, 2024</a>) and can be easily adapted. Developers looking to systematically generate or review more efficient code can embed such prompts directly or apply them as persistent settings.</p>

<h3 id="green-coding-checklist-for-embedding-or-uploading">Green Coding Checklist (for Embedding or Uploading)</h3>

<p>Here is a list of Green Coding Principles that can be incorporated in various ways within ChatGPT: directly in prompts, as system instructions in a custom GPT, or as a Markdown file uploaded during a conversation. This checklist can of course be refined or extended for project-specific needs:</p>

<h3> Green Coding Guidelines for Energy-Efficient Software</h3>
<h4> General Principles</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Use efficient algorithms &amp; data structures</li>
  <li>Avoid redundant computations</li>
  <li>Apply caching &amp; memoization</li>
  <li>Avoid busy-waiting</li>
  <li>Keep memory usage low</li>
  <li>Parallelize tasks sensibly</li>
</ul>
<h4> Python-Specific</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Use vectorized NumPy operations instead of loops</li>
  <li>Prefer generators over lists</li>
  <li>Read files line by line</li>
  <li>Avoid object instantiation inside loops</li>
</ul>
<h4> Java-Specific</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Avoid object allocations in hot loops</li>
  <li>Use streams instead of full data loads</li>
  <li>Prefer primitive types</li>
  <li>Mark constants with <code>final</code></li>
</ul>
<h4> Cross-Technology</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Move loop conditions outside the loop</li>
  <li>Use optimized libraries</li>
  <li>Choose suitable languages/platforms</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>Language models like ChatGPT can be a powerful <strong>tool for sustainable programming</strong>—provided they are used strategically. Research shows: <strong>Energy-efficient code does not happen by default</strong>. It requires clear instructions, thoughtful context, and the integration of green coding principles into the development process. By leveraging <strong>custom instructions</strong>, <strong>prompting strategies</strong>, or tailored <strong>style guides</strong>, developers can start using the potential of LLMs for sustainable software development today—reducing resource consumption while improving code quality. For more background on the intersection of AI and sustainability, check out the <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/KI">first part of our article series</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit," /><category term="#ki" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the first part of our article series, we explored the tension between Artificial Intelligence and sustainability: How can we ensure that AI is not just resource-intensive, but also contributes to solving ecological problems?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial Intelligence - Between Grand Promises and the Illusion of Innovation</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/KI" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial Intelligence - Between Grand Promises and the Illusion of Innovation" /><published>2025-07-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/KI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/KI"><![CDATA[<p><strong>“AI will reach singularity by 2030.”</strong> This bold claim by OpenAI CEO Sam Altman illustrates the immense hype surrounding artificial intelligence (AI). Indeed, modern AI systems are seen as beacons of hope in nearly every field. In <em>medicine</em>, they are expected to detect diseases earlier and help develop new treatments. In the fight against <em>climate change</em>, they promise to optimize the <em>energy sector</em> and <em>mobility</em>. <em>Education</em> could also be transformed by personalized learning systems. And when it comes to <em>climate adaptation</em>, AI is increasingly used to predict extreme weather events, map risks, and help cities adjust their infrastructure to heatwaves. In short: AI is celebrated as a miracle cure for solving humanity’s most pressing problems.</p>

<p>But this euphoric narrative often overshadows a more fundamental issue: While much attention is paid to AI’s energy and resource consumption, a more crucial question remains—<strong>can AI actually create innovation, or is it merely a tool for reassembling existing knowledge?</strong> Today’s systems like GPT-4 are impressive in producing fluent texts, but they draw entirely on pre-existing data. True creative breakthroughs, scientific paradigm shifts, or disruptive ideas still originate from human intuition, curiosity, and experience.</p>

<p>That’s not to ignore the environmental impact: Training large models consumes vast amounts of energy and leaves behind a significant carbon footprint—training GPT-3 alone emitted around <strong>550 tons of CO₂</strong>. And that’s without accounting for the environmental toll of the required hardware: Specialized chips and servers demand enormous resources and materials—often at the expense of ecosystems and communities in mining regions. While some companies are working on more efficient algorithms and sustainable infrastructure, reality still lags behind these ambitions. Without clear ecological guidelines, technological progress risks continuing at the planet’s expense.</p>

<p>The glowing vision of AI as a universal savior begins to look less like a revolutionary shift and more like a reflection of our existing mindset—only faster.</p>

<h2 id="when-ai-becomes-a-technological-miracle-cure">When AI Becomes a Technological Miracle Cure</h2>

<p>Faced with these contradictions, critical questions arise: <strong>Is AI really the solution to all our modern problems—or are we simply creating new ones?</strong> What <strong>ecological</strong> and <strong>social side effects</strong> accompany the AI boom? And who decides <em>how</em> an AI should solve a problem? One thing is certain: An AI always acts according to the goals and priorities we set for it.</p>

<p>Consider this thought experiment: What if an AI were tasked with achieving <em>climate goals at all costs</em>? In extreme cases, it might weigh human suffering against emission reductions. Whether it prioritizes <em>individual well-being</em> or the <em>collective good</em> depends on the values it has been trained with. The question of <strong>how</strong> AI “thinks” is thus closely tied to societal values, ethical boundaries, and—most importantly—<strong>who defines them</strong>.</p>

<p>A real-world example from the U.S. highlights how societal biases can creep into AI systems: Facial recognition software used by U.S. police forces misidentified several innocent Black men as suspects. The problem wasn’t just technical—it stemmed from biased training data and decisions that reproduced systemic inequalities. Algorithms were significantly less accurate at identifying non-white faces, especially Black individuals. Studies showed that the error rate for Black women reached up to <strong>35%</strong>, compared to under <strong>1%</strong> for white men (<a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/projects/gender-shades/overview/">MIT Media Lab, 2018</a>).</p>

<p>Different priorities and blind spots can lead to radically different “solutions”—from technological efficiency to social redistribution. What’s considered “right” ultimately depends on the worldview and objectives behind a system. AI is therefore not a neutral all-rounder but a <strong>tool</strong> shaped by human assumptions. It cannot think—it merely detects and reproduces patterns from the data it was trained on. As such, it cannot develop its own moral framework or make ethical decisions. These too must be programmed by us. Ethical trade-offs—so essential in many societal debates—are beyond AI’s reach unless explicitly defined by humans.</p>

<p>So who really benefits from this AI revolution—and who is left behind? Right now, it’s primarily large tech companies that control the necessary data and computing power, concentrating influence in the hands of a few. Experts warn that AI development risks becoming monopolized, potentially stifling innovation and increasing global dependency (<a href="https://yalelawandpolicy.org/antimonopoly-approach-governing-artificial-intelligence?utm_source=chatgpt.com">Yale Law &amp; Policy Review, 2024</a>). At the same time, millions of jobs are at risk. A study by Goldman Sachs estimates that up to <strong>300 million jobs</strong> worldwide could be automated or altered by generative AI (<a href="https://www.industryintel.com/news/goldman-sachs-ai-could-replace-up-to-300-million-full-time-jobs-globally-with-administrative-and-legal-sectors-at-highest-risk-generative-ai-marks-leap-in-automation-and-could-increase-global-annual-value-of-goods-or-services-output-by-7--171642439200?utm_source">industry intelligence inc., 2025</a>). Administrative, legal, and routine-heavy office work is especially vulnerable. New professions are emerging—like <em>prompt engineering</em>—but the <strong>social transformations</strong> will be far-reaching. However, this shift is occurring more slowly than anticipated a decade ago (<a href="https://www.oecd.org/publications/ai-outlook/">OECD, 2023</a>), making long-term predictions difficult, both technologically and socially.</p>

<p>And the core issue remains: <strong>Can AI truly innovate—or is it just remixing what already exists?</strong> Many experts argue that today’s models, such as GPT-4, are highly capable pattern recognition machines (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1801.00631">vgl. Marcus &amp; Davis, “Rebooting AI”, 2019</a>). They generate outputs by recombining known information—but without any actual understanding. What’s missing is context, a sense of purpose, or even curiosity.</p>

<p><strong>Genuine innovation</strong>—like the theory of relativity or quantum mechanics—requires paradigm shifts, interdisciplinary thinking, and the courage to challenge established ideas. These abilities are deeply rooted in human cognition and remain impossible to replicate algorithmically. At best, AI can serve as a catalyst or assistive tool—generating hypotheses or speeding up workflows—but not as a true source of disruptive breakthroughs. It remains dependent on human-defined goals, data, and evaluation metrics.</p>

<h2 id="ai-only-works-as-a-tool">AI Only Works as a Tool</h2>

<p>How can AI be expected to solve humanity’s grand challenges if it can’t truly innovate? In many ways, AI risks exacerbating the very inequalities it claims to fix. The climate crisis, for example, is not just an ecological emergency but also a social one. Studies show that wealthier populations contribute far more to global emissions, while poorer communities bear the brunt—facing heatwaves, food insecurity, or lack of adaptive infrastructure (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2025/may/07/two-thirds-of-global-heating-caused-by-richest-study-suggests?utm_source=chatgpt.com">The Guardian, 2025</a>). If AI is primarily deployed for economic optimization and industrial efficiency, these imbalances risk being reinforced. New challenges may emerge—without solving the old ones.</p>

<p>If we accept that AI is not <em>the</em> solution, we must ask: <strong>How can it be part of one?</strong> The key lies in understanding AI as a <strong>tool</strong>. And like any tool, it depends on <strong>how and for what</strong> it is used. Responsible governance is essential—grounded in ethical reflection, fair policies, and the political will to shape AI for the common good.</p>

<p>In practical terms, developers, companies, and institutions have a responsibility to use AI consciously—for instance, to detect climate risks early, promote equitable resource use, or democratize access to knowledge. Even on the technical level, there are levers for change: Developers who engage with the principles of <em>green coding</em> can already contribute to sustainability in small but meaningful ways. AI itself can be used deliberately to make one’s code more sustainable—how exactly that works will be the focus of the <strong>next article in this series</strong> (<a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/KI-II">Green Coding with AI – ChatGPT as a Tool for Sustainable Programming</a>). For a general introduction to the topic, see our article <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/green-coding">„Green coding - sustainability in software development“</a>, and for practical approaches, refer to <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/green-coding-patterns">„Green Coding Patterns - Practical Tips for Energy-Efficient Software“</a>. This way, AI becomes not an end in itself but a building block of a more sustainable digital future. It’s not the technology itself that makes the difference—but our decisions about how we use it.</p>

<p>In the end, AI is not a magic fix. It’s a component of a more sustainable digital future. What makes the difference is not the technology itself—but <strong>our choices in how we use it.</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit," /><category term="#ki" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“AI will reach singularity by 2030.” This bold claim by OpenAI CEO Sam Altman illustrates the immense hype surrounding artificial intelligence (AI). Indeed, modern AI systems are seen as beacons of hope in nearly every field. In medicine, they are expected to detect diseases earlier and help develop new treatments. In the fight against climate change, they promise to optimize the energy sector and mobility. Education could also be transformed by personalized learning systems. And when it comes to climate adaptation, AI is increasingly used to predict extreme weather events, map risks, and help cities adjust their infrastructure to heatwaves. In short: AI is celebrated as a miracle cure for solving humanity’s most pressing problems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green Coding Patterns - Practical Tips for Energy-Efficient Software</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding-patterns" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Coding Patterns - Practical Tips for Energy-Efficient Software" /><published>2025-05-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding-patterns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding-patterns"><![CDATA[<p>As the climate crisis intensifies, the <strong>energy consumption of the IT sector</strong> is drawing increasing attention. According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), severe impacts can only be mitigated through <strong>immediate emission reductions</strong>. IT plays a dual role: on the one hand, digitalization can help reduce emissions in other sectors (<em>green by IT</em>). On the other hand, the industry itself must become more sustainable (<em>green in IT</em>).</p>

<p>Software is at the center of this transformation—because <strong>sustainable software is efficient software</strong>. Every inefficient line of code creates not only technical but also <strong>ecological debt</strong>. Like technical debt, it can impair <strong>long-term maintainability and efficiency</strong>—but with the added impact on <strong>real resources like electricity and CO₂</strong>. The good news: no radical changes are needed—what matters most is a <strong>sharpened awareness</strong> and a few <strong>targeted adjustments</strong>. This article presents practical <strong>Green Coding Patterns</strong> that are easy to integrate into everyday development.</p>

<h2 id="small-levers-big-impact">Small Levers, Big Impact</h2>

<p>Sustainable development doesn’t have to start with a complete overhaul. Often, <strong>small everyday changes</strong>—a different format here, a more conscious decision there—can lead to <strong>measurable effects</strong>. These adjustments act like <strong>levers</strong>: small in effort but large in impact. Many small decisions can significantly <strong>reduce energy consumption across multiple levels</strong>.</p>

<p>Changing behaviors step by step leads to a <strong>new awareness</strong>. What feels like an extra effort today can soon become the <strong>new normal</strong>. The following examples highlight such <strong>small levers with big impact</strong>—immediately applicable and effective for both the environment and system performance.</p>

<h2 id="efficiency-through-reduced-computation">Efficiency Through Reduced Computation</h2>

<p>One of the first levers lies in the <strong>code itself</strong>: the less computational power an application requires, the less energy it consumes. <strong>Avoiding unnecessary calculations</strong> is a key lever—just as a fuel-efficient car uses less gas, efficient code uses less electricity. It’s not about perfection, but about setting clear <strong>priorities for resource use</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Avoid unnecessary processes</strong>: Does every click really need to trigger a new query? Does the entire DOM need to re-render? Smart event handling and caching can prevent excess computation.</li>
  <li><strong>Prefer simple data types</strong>: Integer operations often use less energy than floating-point ones. Small changes in data handling can make a big difference.</li>
  <li><strong>Use precompiled resources</strong>: Bundle and optimize scripts and assets before delivery to reduce computation on end devices.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="transferring-data-efficiently">Transferring Data Efficiently</h2>

<p><strong>Data traffic also consumes energy</strong>—on end devices, in networks, and in data centers. The rule: the less, the better.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Transfer only necessary data</strong>: Keep API responses and database queries focused on essentials.</li>
  <li><strong>Compress files</strong>: Text and image files can often be reduced significantly in size without losing quality.</li>
  <li><strong>Use caching effectively</strong>: Repeated data retrievals can be avoided by storing static content locally or on the server.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="energy-efficient-interfaces-and-ux">Energy-Efficient Interfaces and UX</h2>

<p>The <strong>design of an application</strong> directly influences its energy demand. <strong>User-friendliness and resource efficiency</strong> are not mutually exclusive—they go hand in hand.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Use images efficiently</strong>: Lean formats like WebP and properly scaled media reduce file size and energy consumption.</li>
  <li><strong>Reduce animations</strong>: Visual effects increase GPU usage, especially on mobile devices. Less is more.</li>
  <li><strong>Offer dark mode</strong>: On OLED screens, a dark interface saves energy and improves accessibility.</li>
  <li><strong>Optimize loading times</strong>: Faster loading not only saves energy but also improves user experience.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="using-resources-more-wisely">Using Resources More Wisely</h2>

<p>The <strong>infrastructure</strong> behind an application also holds potential for optimization. The goal is to <strong>scale resources to actual needs</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Scale based on demand</strong>: Systems should automatically adapt to load and scale down during off-peak times.</li>
  <li><strong>Shut down unnecessary environments</strong>: Development and test environments don’t need to run 24/7.</li>
  <li><strong>Use serverless and containers</strong>: These technologies help use hardware more efficiently.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="carbon-aware-coding">Carbon-Aware Coding</h2>

<p>Not all electricity is equally green. CO₂ emissions per kilowatt-hour vary depending on the time of day and grid load—depending on whether <strong>renewable sources like wind and solar</strong> are feeding the grid or whether <strong>fossil fuels</strong> dominate. This is called <strong>carbon intensity</strong>, describing how much carbon dioxide is emitted per kilowatt-hour of electricity. <strong>Carbon-aware coding</strong> takes these variations into account.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Schedule intelligently</strong>: Batch jobs or analyses can be timed to run during periods of <strong>low grid load or lower CO₂ intensity</strong>—for instance, when renewables are abundant. Tools like the Carbon Aware SDK or apps like StromGedacht help identify particularly green times in the grid mix.</li>
  <li><strong>Adapt to device states</strong>: Applications should detect whether a device is in energy-saving mode and adjust their behavior accordingly.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="measuring-and-improving">Measuring and Improving</h2>

<p><strong>Sustainability needs metrics</strong>. Only what is measured can be improved. A <strong>realistic overview</strong> of energy usage is the foundation for meaningful change.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Measure energy consumption</strong>: There are various ways to track how much energy an application uses—through <strong>runtime profiling</strong> or <strong>indirect indicators</strong> like CPU load, runtime, or memory usage. While these proxies aren’t precise, they offer helpful insights. More detailed analysis can be done with specialized tools.</li>
  <li><strong>Use benchmarks</strong>: Standardized metrics like the <strong>Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)</strong> make progress measurable. A practical example is available in the <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/powermetrics">previous article on energy analysis with Powermetrics</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="low-hanging-fruits-saving-energy-on-devices">Low Hanging Fruits: Saving Energy on Devices</h2>

<p>Not all optimization happens in code or infrastructure—<strong>devices themselves</strong> offer opportunities for simple yet effective actions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Activate dark mode</strong>: Especially on OLED screens, this can significantly reduce power usage.</li>
  <li><strong>Reduce screen brightness</strong>: One of the simplest ways to save energy.</li>
  <li><strong>Shut down devices after hours</strong>: Turning off monitors, laptops, and peripherals avoids unnecessary standby power.</li>
  <li><strong>Enable energy-saving modes</strong>: Many operating systems and IDEs offer these features—they’re often just unused.</li>
  <li><strong>Close unused tabs and applications</strong>: Less load on the CPU means less energy consumed.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>These small, easy-to-implement actions</strong> complement structural improvements and make <strong>Green Coding</strong> a <strong>holistic approach</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>One major advantage:</strong> Many of these actions can be implemented <strong>individually</strong>, <strong>without team consensus or lengthy discussions</strong>. Anyone adjusting local power settings or activating energy-saving features can <strong>have an immediate impact</strong>. A portion of the <strong>responsibility</strong>—and <strong>freedom to act</strong>—lies in one’s own hands.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-small-steps-big-difference">Conclusion: Small Steps, Big Difference</h2>

<p><strong>Green Coding doesn’t have to be complex.</strong> Many practices are simple to implement and deliver real impact. <strong>Efficient code</strong>, <strong>reduced data transfer</strong>, and <strong>thoughtful interfaces</strong> help lower energy consumption while making software more <strong>performant and reliable</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Developers have the power</strong> to make software more sustainable—one line at a time.</p>

<p>Want more? You can find strategic background and further insights in the <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/green-coding">article “Green Software, Green Future”</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Marcel, Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the climate crisis intensifies, the energy consumption of the IT sector is drawing increasing attention. According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), severe impacts can only be mitigated through immediate emission reductions. IT plays a dual role: on the one hand, digitalization can help reduce emissions in other sectors (green by IT). On the other hand, the industry itself must become more sustainable (green in IT).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Determine energy consumption - with on-board tools - The self-test for video conferencing tools</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/powermetrics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Determine energy consumption - with on-board tools - The self-test for video conferencing tools" /><published>2025-04-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/powermetrics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/powermetrics"><![CDATA[<h2 id="video-conferencing-tools-compared-how-much-energy-do-zoom-teams-and-facetime-really-use">Video Conferencing Tools Compared: How Much Energy Do Zoom, Teams, and FaceTime Really Use?</h2>

<p>Video conferencing has become an integral part of our everyday lives. But how climate-friendly are tools like Zoom, Teams, and FaceTime really? In a self-experiment, all three tools were tested under identical conditions – with some surprising results.</p>

<p>This wasn’t just about the tools themselves, but also about a central question: Can the energy consumption of digital applications be measured and compared with simple methods? The answer is: <strong>Yes.</strong> Using the built-in <strong>powermetrics</strong> tool available on every Mac and some scripting in <strong>Python</strong>, a realistic test setup was created. It shows that even without expensive hardware or specialized software, meaningful energy comparisons are possible. The experiment proves that solid insights into energy efficiency can be achieved in a <strong>low-threshold and reproducible</strong> way – an important aspect for IT professionals who take sustainability seriously in their digital infrastructure.</p>

<h2 id="setup-and-objective">Setup and Objective</h2>

<p>The self-experiment was conducted in <strong>June/July 2023</strong> on a <strong>MacBookPro17,1 running macOS Ventura Version 13.3</strong>. Only the energy consumption on the device itself was considered – meaning the energy demand of each application on the MacBook, excluding network usage or external infrastructure. The three widely used video conferencing tools <strong>Zoom</strong>, <strong>Microsoft Teams</strong>, and <strong>FaceTime</strong> were tested. The goal was to examine how incoming and outgoing video and screen sharing impact energy consumption – and whether recommendations for more sustainable usage can be derived.</p>

<p>At the same time, the experiment aimed to demonstrate that tools like <strong>powermetrics</strong>, a <strong>Python script</strong>, and a well-designed test setup can already be used to make qualitative statements about energy efficiency.</p>

<h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2>

<p>Each tool was tested in various scenarios: <strong>incoming video on/off, outgoing video on/off, and screen sharing on/off</strong>. The so-called <strong>Energy Impact</strong> was recorded – a model value generated by powermetrics and saved as a text file. A <strong>restart</strong> was performed before each measurement series to terminate unnecessary processes. Additionally, a <strong>baseline</strong> was established by modeling the Energy Impact after a restart with no programs open.</p>

<p>Measurements were conducted in <strong>10-minute blocks</strong>. Each scenario was repeated <strong>three times</strong>, and the <strong>average Energy Impact</strong> was calculated.</p>

<p>The analysis script was written in <strong>Python</strong>: relevant data was extracted using <strong>regex</strong>, transferred to a <strong>Pandas DataFrame</strong>, and <strong>visualized</strong>.</p>

<p>The test setup was intentionally kept <strong>realistic</strong>: video calls were conducted between two laptops. An external display showed a standardized test video with audio, which was recorded by the MacBook’s camera. This ensured that all scenarios were <strong>consistent and reproducible</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="results-overview">Results Overview</h2>

<p>The two charts below clearly show the average Energy Impact of the tested video conferencing tools in two groups of scenarios: with and without screen sharing. This makes it easy to visually compare the energy profiles of the applications.</p>

<p>The results reveal clear differences between the tools – especially with screen sharing and active video. <strong>Microsoft Teams</strong> performed <strong>worse in almost all scenarios</strong> compared to Zoom and FaceTime. Only in the <strong>minimal mode without video or screen sharing</strong> were the results across all tools relatively similar.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/mit-screen-sharing-en.png" alt="Energy Impact with screen sharing" /></p>

<p>These data clearly show: <strong>The choice of tool and video conference configuration has a direct impact on energy consumption.</strong> Especially for regular meetings, it’s worth being mindful about camera and screen sharing behavior – particularly when using Teams.</p>

<p>A particularly revealing comparison is between the “everything off” and “everything on” scenarios. While FaceTime and Zoom showed almost identical values with only incoming or outgoing video compared to the “everything off” scenario, Microsoft Teams showed a dramatic difference: <strong>Energy Impact increased by a factor of 80</strong> when all features – incoming and outgoing video and screen sharing – were enabled. In comparison: FaceTime’s consumption only increased by about <strong>a factor of five</strong>, Zoom by <strong>a factor of three</strong>. This not only highlights the technical efficiency of each platform, but also the immense potential for optimization through conscious use.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/ohne-screen-sharing-en.png" alt="Energy Impact without screen sharing" /></p>

<p>In the scenario with all features enabled (<strong>“Video in/out + screen sharing on”</strong>), the <strong>Energy Impact for Teams was about three times higher</strong> than in minimal mode with everything disabled – a significant difference that adds up over time.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-understanding-energy-use--a-foundation-for-sustainable-software">Conclusion: Understanding Energy Use – A Foundation for Sustainable Software</h2>

<p>The self-experiment shows <strong>just how wide the differences in energy consumption</strong> between video conferencing tools can be. Even with <strong>basic built-in tools</strong>, <strong>meaningful results</strong> can be achieved. This approach makes it possible to <strong>gradually engage with the complex topic of software energy efficiency</strong> – without immediately needing specialized measurement equipment or large resources.</p>

<p>The insights gained provide a <strong>solid foundation</strong> for evaluating software in terms of energy efficiency – and build a bridge to the <strong>Software Carbon Intensity (SCI) standard</strong>, which focuses on the <strong>transparent measurement and optimization of CO₂ emissions from software</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>With the right tool and more conscious usage, even everyday applications can be used more sustainably.</strong></p>

<p>For a deeper dive into the topic, check out our dedicated article on the <strong><a href="https://mehrwert.tech/SCI">Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)</a></strong> standard and how it enables consistent CO₂ assessments for software.</p>

<p>Also recommended: our <strong><a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">article series on Embodied Carbon</a></strong>, which explores the <strong>hidden emissions in the hardware lifecycle</strong> – a crucial counterpart to the software perspective.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Video Conferencing Tools Compared: How Much Energy Do Zoom, Teams, and FaceTime Really Use?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carbon Intensity software - making sustainability measurable</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/SCI" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carbon Intensity software - making sustainability measurable" /><published>2025-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/SCI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/SCI"><![CDATA[<p>Sustainability is no longer just a buzzword – its ecological, economic, and social impacts are becoming increasingly relevant in software development. As we’ve already explored in our <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/software-obsoleszenz">previous article</a>, software decisions can significantly affect hardware longevity.</p>

<p>In this post, we focus on an approach that makes the <strong>energy consumption of software itself</strong> and its related CO₂ emissions visible. The <strong>Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)</strong> standard, developed by the Green Software Foundation, helps developers and companies model the emissions of their applications and supports them in making more conscious decisions.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-software-carbon-intensity-sci">What is Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)?</h2>

<p>SCI brings transparency to the environmental impact of software and provides a simple formula and clear methodology to estimate CO₂ emissions. The goal is to create an objective and repeatable foundation for making software more <strong>ecologically</strong> sustainable.</p>

<h2 id="how-sci-works">How SCI Works</h2>

<p>SCI models the CO₂ emissions caused both during operation and in the creation of software. This includes <em>energy consumption</em>, <em>hardware efficiency</em>, and the <em>energy mix</em>. It gives developers the transparency they need to pinpoint the areas with the greatest potential for effective carbon reduction.</p>

<p>The core formula of SCI is:</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/SCI.png" alt="Formula of Software Carbon Intensity" />
<small> <a href="https://learn.greensoftware.foundation/measurement/">Green Software Foundation</a></small></p>

<p>In this formula, <em>E</em> represents the energy consumed by the software in kWh, <em>I</em> the amount of CO₂ per kWh consumed, and <em>M</em> the embodied carbon. (To learn more about what embodied carbon means and how it’s measured, check out our series on <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">Embodied Carbon</a>). The factor <em>R</em> normalizes these emissions per use, user, system runtime, or access – depending on the context and availability of data. In Germany, the average value for <em>I</em> in 2023 was 380 g CO₂/kWh (Umweltbundesamt, 2023). Further values and country-specific data can be found at <a href="https://app.electricitymaps.com/">electricityMaps</a> or the <a href="https://www.iea.org/data-and-statistics/data-browser?country=WORLD\&amp;fuel=Energy%20consumption\&amp;indicator=Electricity%20generation%20by%20source">IEA</a>.</p>

<p>A practical example for measuring energy consumption is modeling via CPU and RAM usage. Alternatively, energy can be estimated using network load, number and type of processes, or standardized benchmark tests. The chosen methods must always be well-documented and reproducible to ensure transparency. A physical power meter isn’t strictly necessary – script-based tools like Apple’s “powermetrics” can reliably estimate actual hardware utilization.</p>

<h2 id="an-internationally-recognized-iso-standard">An Internationally Recognized ISO Standard</h2>

<p>Since 2024, SCI has been officially recognized as an ISO standard (ISO/IEC 21031:2024). It defines clear criteria and methods for transparently measuring and reporting the carbon footprint of software. As a result, it has gained international relevance and acceptance, making it easier to implement across the industry. Companies benefit from a globally accepted framework that enables consistent and comparable sustainability assessments.</p>

<h2 id="measuring-is-winning">Measuring is Winning</h2>

<p>SCI allows companies to compare the environmental efficiency of different software solutions and make informed, sustainable choices. Developers integrate the methodology directly into their workflows, leading to more resource-efficient products in the long term (Green Software Foundation Projects, 2024). Solid data is essential here – because you can only improve what you can measure. SCI provides this data, creating the foundation for real transparency and actionable sustainability in software development.</p>

<h2 id="challenges-and-criticism">Challenges and Criticism</h2>

<p>Implementing a new standard comes with its challenges. Accurate measurements rely on high-quality data, which can be time-consuming to collect. To make SCI truly effective, it needs to be put into practice and backed by real-world examples. Even rough estimates are enough to trigger improvements and identify the most impactful areas for reducing emissions.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>The Software Carbon Intensity standard sets a new benchmark for sustainable software development. With clear, measurable outcomes, it empowers organizations and developers to take meaningful action on emissions. Now it’s up to the industry to adopt the standard and drive real change for a more sustainable digital future. For more insights into hardware-related emissions, check out our series on <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">Embodied Carbon</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sustainability is no longer just a buzzword – its ecological, economic, and social impacts are becoming increasingly relevant in software development. As we’ve already explored in our previous article, software decisions can significantly affect hardware longevity.]]></summary></entry></feed>