<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-05-23T12:55:20+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/index.xml</id><title type="html">page_title</title><subtitle>page_description</subtitle><author><name>mehr.wert Software und IT Beratung GmbH</name></author><entry><title type="html">Green Coding Patterns - Practical Tips for Energy-Efficient Software</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding-patterns" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Coding Patterns - Practical Tips for Energy-Efficient Software" /><published>2025-05-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding-patterns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding-patterns"><![CDATA[<p>As the climate crisis intensifies, the <strong>energy consumption of the IT sector</strong> is drawing increasing attention. According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), severe impacts can only be mitigated through <strong>immediate emission reductions</strong>. IT plays a dual role: on the one hand, digitalization can help reduce emissions in other sectors (<em>green by IT</em>). On the other hand, the industry itself must become more sustainable (<em>green in IT</em>).</p>

<p>Software is at the center of this transformation—because <strong>sustainable software is efficient software</strong>. Every inefficient line of code creates not only technical but also <strong>ecological debt</strong>. Like technical debt, it can impair <strong>long-term maintainability and efficiency</strong>—but with the added impact on <strong>real resources like electricity and CO₂</strong>. The good news: no radical changes are needed—what matters most is a <strong>sharpened awareness</strong> and a few <strong>targeted adjustments</strong>. This article presents practical <strong>Green Coding Patterns</strong> that are easy to integrate into everyday development.</p>

<h2 id="small-levers-big-impact">Small Levers, Big Impact</h2>

<p>Sustainable development doesn’t have to start with a complete overhaul. Often, <strong>small everyday changes</strong>—a different format here, a more conscious decision there—can lead to <strong>measurable effects</strong>. These adjustments act like <strong>levers</strong>: small in effort but large in impact. Many small decisions can significantly <strong>reduce energy consumption across multiple levels</strong>.</p>

<p>Changing behaviors step by step leads to a <strong>new awareness</strong>. What feels like an extra effort today can soon become the <strong>new normal</strong>. The following examples highlight such <strong>small levers with big impact</strong>—immediately applicable and effective for both the environment and system performance.</p>

<h2 id="efficiency-through-reduced-computation">Efficiency Through Reduced Computation</h2>

<p>One of the first levers lies in the <strong>code itself</strong>: the less computational power an application requires, the less energy it consumes. <strong>Avoiding unnecessary calculations</strong> is a key lever—just as a fuel-efficient car uses less gas, efficient code uses less electricity. It’s not about perfection, but about setting clear <strong>priorities for resource use</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Avoid unnecessary processes</strong>: Does every click really need to trigger a new query? Does the entire DOM need to re-render? Smart event handling and caching can prevent excess computation.</li>
  <li><strong>Prefer simple data types</strong>: Integer operations often use less energy than floating-point ones. Small changes in data handling can make a big difference.</li>
  <li><strong>Use precompiled resources</strong>: Bundle and optimize scripts and assets before delivery to reduce computation on end devices.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="transferring-data-efficiently">Transferring Data Efficiently</h2>

<p><strong>Data traffic also consumes energy</strong>—on end devices, in networks, and in data centers. The rule: the less, the better.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Transfer only necessary data</strong>: Keep API responses and database queries focused on essentials.</li>
  <li><strong>Compress files</strong>: Text and image files can often be reduced significantly in size without losing quality.</li>
  <li><strong>Use caching effectively</strong>: Repeated data retrievals can be avoided by storing static content locally or on the server.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="energy-efficient-interfaces-and-ux">Energy-Efficient Interfaces and UX</h2>

<p>The <strong>design of an application</strong> directly influences its energy demand. <strong>User-friendliness and resource efficiency</strong> are not mutually exclusive—they go hand in hand.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Use images efficiently</strong>: Lean formats like WebP and properly scaled media reduce file size and energy consumption.</li>
  <li><strong>Reduce animations</strong>: Visual effects increase GPU usage, especially on mobile devices. Less is more.</li>
  <li><strong>Offer dark mode</strong>: On OLED screens, a dark interface saves energy and improves accessibility.</li>
  <li><strong>Optimize loading times</strong>: Faster loading not only saves energy but also improves user experience.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="using-resources-more-wisely">Using Resources More Wisely</h2>

<p>The <strong>infrastructure</strong> behind an application also holds potential for optimization. The goal is to <strong>scale resources to actual needs</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Scale based on demand</strong>: Systems should automatically adapt to load and scale down during off-peak times.</li>
  <li><strong>Shut down unnecessary environments</strong>: Development and test environments don’t need to run 24/7.</li>
  <li><strong>Use serverless and containers</strong>: These technologies help use hardware more efficiently.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="carbon-aware-coding">Carbon-Aware Coding</h2>

<p>Not all electricity is equally green. CO₂ emissions per kilowatt-hour vary depending on the time of day and grid load—depending on whether <strong>renewable sources like wind and solar</strong> are feeding the grid or whether <strong>fossil fuels</strong> dominate. This is called <strong>carbon intensity</strong>, describing how much carbon dioxide is emitted per kilowatt-hour of electricity. <strong>Carbon-aware coding</strong> takes these variations into account.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Schedule intelligently</strong>: Batch jobs or analyses can be timed to run during periods of <strong>low grid load or lower CO₂ intensity</strong>—for instance, when renewables are abundant. Tools like the Carbon Aware SDK or apps like StromGedacht help identify particularly green times in the grid mix.</li>
  <li><strong>Adapt to device states</strong>: Applications should detect whether a device is in energy-saving mode and adjust their behavior accordingly.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="measuring-and-improving">Measuring and Improving</h2>

<p><strong>Sustainability needs metrics</strong>. Only what is measured can be improved. A <strong>realistic overview</strong> of energy usage is the foundation for meaningful change.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Measure energy consumption</strong>: There are various ways to track how much energy an application uses—through <strong>runtime profiling</strong> or <strong>indirect indicators</strong> like CPU load, runtime, or memory usage. While these proxies aren’t precise, they offer helpful insights. More detailed analysis can be done with specialized tools.</li>
  <li><strong>Use benchmarks</strong>: Standardized metrics like the <strong>Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)</strong> make progress measurable. A practical example is available in the <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/powermetrics">previous article on energy analysis with Powermetrics</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="low-hanging-fruits-saving-energy-on-devices">Low Hanging Fruits: Saving Energy on Devices</h2>

<p>Not all optimization happens in code or infrastructure—<strong>devices themselves</strong> offer opportunities for simple yet effective actions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Activate dark mode</strong>: Especially on OLED screens, this can significantly reduce power usage.</li>
  <li><strong>Reduce screen brightness</strong>: One of the simplest ways to save energy.</li>
  <li><strong>Shut down devices after hours</strong>: Turning off monitors, laptops, and peripherals avoids unnecessary standby power.</li>
  <li><strong>Enable energy-saving modes</strong>: Many operating systems and IDEs offer these features—they’re often just unused.</li>
  <li><strong>Close unused tabs and applications</strong>: Less load on the CPU means less energy consumed.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>These small, easy-to-implement actions</strong> complement structural improvements and make <strong>Green Coding</strong> a <strong>holistic approach</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>One major advantage:</strong> Many of these actions can be implemented <strong>individually</strong>, <strong>without team consensus or lengthy discussions</strong>. Anyone adjusting local power settings or activating energy-saving features can <strong>have an immediate impact</strong>. A portion of the <strong>responsibility</strong>—and <strong>freedom to act</strong>—lies in one’s own hands.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-small-steps-big-difference">Conclusion: Small Steps, Big Difference</h2>

<p><strong>Green Coding doesn’t have to be complex.</strong> Many practices are simple to implement and deliver real impact. <strong>Efficient code</strong>, <strong>reduced data transfer</strong>, and <strong>thoughtful interfaces</strong> help lower energy consumption while making software more <strong>performant and reliable</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Developers have the power</strong> to make software more sustainable—one line at a time.</p>

<p>Want more? You can find strategic background and further insights in the <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/green-coding">article “Green Software, Green Future”</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Marcel, Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the climate crisis intensifies, the energy consumption of the IT sector is drawing increasing attention. According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), severe impacts can only be mitigated through immediate emission reductions. IT plays a dual role: on the one hand, digitalization can help reduce emissions in other sectors (green by IT). On the other hand, the industry itself must become more sustainable (green in IT).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Determine energy consumption - with on-board tools - The self-test for video conferencing tools</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/powermetrics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Determine energy consumption - with on-board tools - The self-test for video conferencing tools" /><published>2025-04-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/powermetrics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/powermetrics"><![CDATA[<h2 id="video-conferencing-tools-compared-how-much-energy-do-zoom-teams-and-facetime-really-use">Video Conferencing Tools Compared: How Much Energy Do Zoom, Teams, and FaceTime Really Use?</h2>

<p>Video conferencing has become an integral part of our everyday lives. But how climate-friendly are tools like Zoom, Teams, and FaceTime really? In a self-experiment, all three tools were tested under identical conditions – with some surprising results.</p>

<p>This wasn’t just about the tools themselves, but also about a central question: Can the energy consumption of digital applications be measured and compared with simple methods? The answer is: <strong>Yes.</strong> Using the built-in <strong>powermetrics</strong> tool available on every Mac and some scripting in <strong>Python</strong>, a realistic test setup was created. It shows that even without expensive hardware or specialized software, meaningful energy comparisons are possible. The experiment proves that solid insights into energy efficiency can be achieved in a <strong>low-threshold and reproducible</strong> way – an important aspect for IT professionals who take sustainability seriously in their digital infrastructure.</p>

<h2 id="setup-and-objective">Setup and Objective</h2>

<p>The self-experiment was conducted in <strong>June/July 2023</strong> on a <strong>MacBookPro17,1 running macOS Ventura Version 13.3</strong>. Only the energy consumption on the device itself was considered – meaning the energy demand of each application on the MacBook, excluding network usage or external infrastructure. The three widely used video conferencing tools <strong>Zoom</strong>, <strong>Microsoft Teams</strong>, and <strong>FaceTime</strong> were tested. The goal was to examine how incoming and outgoing video and screen sharing impact energy consumption – and whether recommendations for more sustainable usage can be derived.</p>

<p>At the same time, the experiment aimed to demonstrate that tools like <strong>powermetrics</strong>, a <strong>Python script</strong>, and a well-designed test setup can already be used to make qualitative statements about energy efficiency.</p>

<h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2>

<p>Each tool was tested in various scenarios: <strong>incoming video on/off, outgoing video on/off, and screen sharing on/off</strong>. The so-called <strong>Energy Impact</strong> was recorded – a model value generated by powermetrics and saved as a text file. A <strong>restart</strong> was performed before each measurement series to terminate unnecessary processes. Additionally, a <strong>baseline</strong> was established by modeling the Energy Impact after a restart with no programs open.</p>

<p>Measurements were conducted in <strong>10-minute blocks</strong>. Each scenario was repeated <strong>three times</strong>, and the <strong>average Energy Impact</strong> was calculated.</p>

<p>The analysis script was written in <strong>Python</strong>: relevant data was extracted using <strong>regex</strong>, transferred to a <strong>Pandas DataFrame</strong>, and <strong>visualized</strong>.</p>

<p>The test setup was intentionally kept <strong>realistic</strong>: video calls were conducted between two laptops. An external display showed a standardized test video with audio, which was recorded by the MacBook’s camera. This ensured that all scenarios were <strong>consistent and reproducible</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="results-overview">Results Overview</h2>

<p>The two charts below clearly show the average Energy Impact of the tested video conferencing tools in two groups of scenarios: with and without screen sharing. This makes it easy to visually compare the energy profiles of the applications.</p>

<p>The results reveal clear differences between the tools – especially with screen sharing and active video. <strong>Microsoft Teams</strong> performed <strong>worse in almost all scenarios</strong> compared to Zoom and FaceTime. Only in the <strong>minimal mode without video or screen sharing</strong> were the results across all tools relatively similar.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/mit-screen-sharing-en.png" alt="Energy Impact with screen sharing" /></p>

<p>These data clearly show: <strong>The choice of tool and video conference configuration has a direct impact on energy consumption.</strong> Especially for regular meetings, it’s worth being mindful about camera and screen sharing behavior – particularly when using Teams.</p>

<p>A particularly revealing comparison is between the “everything off” and “everything on” scenarios. While FaceTime and Zoom showed almost identical values with only incoming or outgoing video compared to the “everything off” scenario, Microsoft Teams showed a dramatic difference: <strong>Energy Impact increased by a factor of 80</strong> when all features – incoming and outgoing video and screen sharing – were enabled. In comparison: FaceTime’s consumption only increased by about <strong>a factor of five</strong>, Zoom by <strong>a factor of three</strong>. This not only highlights the technical efficiency of each platform, but also the immense potential for optimization through conscious use.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/ohne-screen-sharing-en.png" alt="Energy Impact without screen sharing" /></p>

<p>In the scenario with all features enabled (<strong>“Video in/out + screen sharing on”</strong>), the <strong>Energy Impact for Teams was about three times higher</strong> than in minimal mode with everything disabled – a significant difference that adds up over time.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-understanding-energy-use--a-foundation-for-sustainable-software">Conclusion: Understanding Energy Use – A Foundation for Sustainable Software</h2>

<p>The self-experiment shows <strong>just how wide the differences in energy consumption</strong> between video conferencing tools can be. Even with <strong>basic built-in tools</strong>, <strong>meaningful results</strong> can be achieved. This approach makes it possible to <strong>gradually engage with the complex topic of software energy efficiency</strong> – without immediately needing specialized measurement equipment or large resources.</p>

<p>The insights gained provide a <strong>solid foundation</strong> for evaluating software in terms of energy efficiency – and build a bridge to the <strong>Software Carbon Intensity (SCI) standard</strong>, which focuses on the <strong>transparent measurement and optimization of CO₂ emissions from software</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>With the right tool and more conscious usage, even everyday applications can be used more sustainably.</strong></p>

<p>For a deeper dive into the topic, check out our dedicated article on the <strong><a href="https://mehrwert.tech/SCI">Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)</a></strong> standard and how it enables consistent CO₂ assessments for software.</p>

<p>Also recommended: our <strong><a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">article series on Embodied Carbon</a></strong>, which explores the <strong>hidden emissions in the hardware lifecycle</strong> – a crucial counterpart to the software perspective.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Video Conferencing Tools Compared: How Much Energy Do Zoom, Teams, and FaceTime Really Use?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carbon Intensity software - making sustainability measurable</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/SCI" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carbon Intensity software - making sustainability measurable" /><published>2025-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/SCI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/SCI"><![CDATA[<p>Sustainability is no longer just a buzzword – its ecological, economic, and social impacts are becoming increasingly relevant in software development. As we’ve already explored in our <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/software-obsoleszenz">previous article</a>, software decisions can significantly affect hardware longevity.</p>

<p>In this post, we focus on an approach that makes the <strong>energy consumption of software itself</strong> and its related CO₂ emissions visible. The <strong>Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)</strong> standard, developed by the Green Software Foundation, helps developers and companies model the emissions of their applications and supports them in making more conscious decisions.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-software-carbon-intensity-sci">What is Software Carbon Intensity (SCI)?</h2>

<p>SCI brings transparency to the environmental impact of software and provides a simple formula and clear methodology to estimate CO₂ emissions. The goal is to create an objective and repeatable foundation for making software more <strong>ecologically</strong> sustainable.</p>

<h2 id="how-sci-works">How SCI Works</h2>

<p>SCI models the CO₂ emissions caused both during operation and in the creation of software. This includes <em>energy consumption</em>, <em>hardware efficiency</em>, and the <em>energy mix</em>. It gives developers the transparency they need to pinpoint the areas with the greatest potential for effective carbon reduction.</p>

<p>The core formula of SCI is:</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/SCI.png" alt="Formula of Software Carbon Intensity" />
<small> <a href="https://learn.greensoftware.foundation/measurement/">Green Software Foundation</a></small></p>

<p>In this formula, <em>E</em> represents the energy consumed by the software in kWh, <em>I</em> the amount of CO₂ per kWh consumed, and <em>M</em> the embodied carbon. (To learn more about what embodied carbon means and how it’s measured, check out our series on <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">Embodied Carbon</a>). The factor <em>R</em> normalizes these emissions per use, user, system runtime, or access – depending on the context and availability of data. In Germany, the average value for <em>I</em> in 2023 was 380 g CO₂/kWh (Umweltbundesamt, 2023). Further values and country-specific data can be found at <a href="https://app.electricitymaps.com/">electricityMaps</a> or the <a href="https://www.iea.org/data-and-statistics/data-browser?country=WORLD\&amp;fuel=Energy%20consumption\&amp;indicator=Electricity%20generation%20by%20source">IEA</a>.</p>

<p>A practical example for measuring energy consumption is modeling via CPU and RAM usage. Alternatively, energy can be estimated using network load, number and type of processes, or standardized benchmark tests. The chosen methods must always be well-documented and reproducible to ensure transparency. A physical power meter isn’t strictly necessary – script-based tools like Apple’s “powermetrics” can reliably estimate actual hardware utilization.</p>

<h2 id="an-internationally-recognized-iso-standard">An Internationally Recognized ISO Standard</h2>

<p>Since 2024, SCI has been officially recognized as an ISO standard (ISO/IEC 21031:2024). It defines clear criteria and methods for transparently measuring and reporting the carbon footprint of software. As a result, it has gained international relevance and acceptance, making it easier to implement across the industry. Companies benefit from a globally accepted framework that enables consistent and comparable sustainability assessments.</p>

<h2 id="measuring-is-winning">Measuring is Winning</h2>

<p>SCI allows companies to compare the environmental efficiency of different software solutions and make informed, sustainable choices. Developers integrate the methodology directly into their workflows, leading to more resource-efficient products in the long term (Green Software Foundation Projects, 2024). Solid data is essential here – because you can only improve what you can measure. SCI provides this data, creating the foundation for real transparency and actionable sustainability in software development.</p>

<h2 id="challenges-and-criticism">Challenges and Criticism</h2>

<p>Implementing a new standard comes with its challenges. Accurate measurements rely on high-quality data, which can be time-consuming to collect. To make SCI truly effective, it needs to be put into practice and backed by real-world examples. Even rough estimates are enough to trigger improvements and identify the most impactful areas for reducing emissions.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>The Software Carbon Intensity standard sets a new benchmark for sustainable software development. With clear, measurable outcomes, it empowers organizations and developers to take meaningful action on emissions. Now it’s up to the industry to adopt the standard and drive real change for a more sustainable digital future. For more insights into hardware-related emissions, check out our series on <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">Embodied Carbon</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sustainability is no longer just a buzzword – its ecological, economic, and social impacts are becoming increasingly relevant in software development. As we’ve already explored in our previous article, software decisions can significantly affect hardware longevity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Software Influences Hardware Lifespan</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/software-bsoleszenz" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Software Influences Hardware Lifespan" /><published>2025-03-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/en/software-bsoleszenz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/en/software-bsoleszenz"><![CDATA[<p>In the IT world, a device’s lifespan is not determined solely by hardware quality—<strong>software plays a crucial role</strong> as well. Many hardware components are discarded today even though they are still technically functional. The reason? Modern software places ever <strong>higher demands on processors, memory, and other resources</strong>. Industry analyses show that increasing software requirements drive hardware replacements more than pure technological innovation. This dynamic has significant implications for companies aiming to manage their IT infrastructure <strong>efficiently, cost-effectively, and sustainably</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="software-as-the-key-to-hardware-longevity">Software as the Key to Hardware Longevity</h2>

<p>Software largely determines <strong>how long hardware remains usable</strong>. Functional hardware is often <strong>replaced prematurely</strong> because rising software demands make it obsolete—a phenomenon known as <strong>software obsolescence</strong>. As the technological gap between hardware generations narrows, software—not hardware innovation—has become the primary driver of increasing electronic waste. Lack of software support or compatibility with newer programs renders older devices practically useless, even when the hardware is still functional. This form of software-driven aging leads to hardware being discarded before reaching its full technical lifespan. Moreover, it makes <strong>refurbishment options less attractive or even impossible</strong>, as older devices can no longer be effectively reused due to compatibility issues with modern software. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planned_obsolescence">[Wikipedia]</a></p>

<h2 id="consequences-and-challenges">Consequences and Challenges</h2>

<p><strong>Software obsolescence</strong> forces companies to <strong>replace hardware more frequently</strong>, increasing investment costs and contradicting sustainability goals. According to a study by the European Environmental Bureau (EEB), extending the lifespan of computers by just one year could reduce the environmental impact of these devices by approximately 25%. <a href="https://eeb.org/revealed-the-climate-cost-of-disposable-smartphones/">[EEB, 2019]</a> Manufacturers must design software, products, and services to ensure <strong>long-term support and compatibility</strong>, allowing hardware to remain in use for longer periods.</p>

<h2 id="strategies-for-extending-hardware-lifespan">Strategies for Extending Hardware Lifespan</h2>

<p>Companies can extend the lifespan of their hardware through conscious decisions in software development and selection. It is essential to prioritize software products whose vendors guarantee <strong>long-term support (LTS) versions</strong>. This reduces the need for frequent hardware replacements while ensuring prolonged usability. Products that utilize <strong>open interfaces and standard formats</strong> enable better integration with older systems and offer long-term flexibility for software updates and modifications. To help customers make informed decisions, vendors must provide <strong>transparent communication</strong> regarding product support duration, hardware requirements, and long-term compatibility.</p>

<p>A recent example is the Google Pixel 9, which has been announced with guaranteed security updates until at least October 2033. Additionally, Google has clearly communicated the hardware specifications necessary for long-term usage. <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Pixel-9a-Googles-Antwort-auf-das-Apple-iPhone-16e-10321170.html">[Heise, 2025]</a> This transparency allows businesses to plan their IT infrastructure more reliably.</p>

<p>Furthermore, software updates should not artificially degrade older hardware performance through intentional slowdowns or exclusion from new versions. <strong>Transparent and fair update strategies</strong> promote longer hardware lifecycles. The use of <strong>open-source software</strong> also extends hardware lifespan, as the community continuously develops and adapts solutions for older devices. Companies should also plan hardware upgrades <strong>based on actual needs</strong>, utilizing modern monitoring tools to assess performance accurately and prevent unnecessary investments.</p>

<h3 id="development-of-security-updates-for-smartphones">Development of Security Updates for Smartphones</h3>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/Security Update Duration of Apple iPhones and Google Pixel Smartphones.png" alt="Duration of Security Updates for iPhones and Google Pixel Smartphones" />
<small> <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Softwareaktualisierung#Google">Wikipedia Google</a>, <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPhone">Wikipedia iPhone</a></small></p>

<p>The chart illustrates the increasing length of guaranteed security updates for iPhone and Google Pixel models over recent years. This trend is highly positive, as extended update periods improve device usability and security. Businesses and users must now adapt to these improved and more sustainable usage cycles and adjust their IT strategies accordingly.</p>

<h2 id="how-software-developers-can-promote-hardware-longevity">How Software Developers Can Promote Hardware Longevity</h2>

<p>Software developers play a crucial role in extending hardware lifespan. <strong>Resource-efficient programming</strong> helps by optimizing algorithms, minimizing background processes, and reducing memory usage. Particularly memory-intensive tasks or unnecessary graphical effects should be optional and adjustable to avoid excessive strain on older hardware. Developers should also ensure <strong>long-term compatibility</strong> by regularly testing software on older hardware generations and operating systems.</p>

<p>Supporting <strong>backward compatibility</strong> is essential, ensuring that updates do not exclude older devices. Applications should be designed in a modular and scalable way so that resource-intensive features are only activated if the hardware can handle them. This allows users with older devices to continue enjoying a good user experience without being forced to upgrade. Each new feature should be critically evaluated for its actual value, as unnecessary additions can significantly burden hardware.</p>

<p>Additionally, developers should adopt <strong>sustainable update strategies</strong>, separating security updates from feature enhancements. This allows users to keep older devices secure without being forced to install resource-heavy new functionalities. Whenever possible, developers should use <strong>open standards and open-source components</strong> to ensure long-term software maintenance by the community.</p>

<h2 id="benefits-of-extending-hardware-lifespan">Benefits of Extending Hardware Lifespan</h2>

<p>Extending hardware lifespan offers clear advantages for businesses. It leads to <strong>significant cost savings</strong>, as fewer hardware purchases ease IT budgets while reducing maintenance, setup, and disposal costs. Sustainable IT practices contribute to less electronic waste, lower resource consumption, and an improved carbon footprint, strengthening a company’s environmental reputation. Additionally, <strong>competitive advantages</strong> arise as sustainable IT strategies enhance corporate image and increase customer loyalty, especially as more consumers and partners prioritize ecological responsibility.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>By managing software requirements wisely and implementing strategic software development approaches, businesses can significantly extend hardware lifespan. This leads to financial benefits while making a meaningful contribution to environmental sustainability. Given the substantial environmental impact of hardware production—also known as <strong>embodied carbon</strong> (more on this in our article series on <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/embodied-carbon-1"><strong>Embodied Carbon</strong></a> )—extending hardware lifespan is essential.</p>

<p>Software developers and companies can further contribute through *<a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/trainings/gsp.html"><strong>Green Coding</strong></a>, which promotes sustainable software practices. The responsibility ultimately lies with manufacturers, developers, and businesses to make sustainable IT decisions that foster long-term, efficient, and resource-conscious infrastructure usage.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina, Marcel</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the IT world, a device’s lifespan is not determined solely by hardware quality—software plays a crucial role as well. Many hardware components are discarded today even though they are still technically functional. The reason? Modern software places ever higher demands on processors, memory, and other resources. Industry analyses show that increasing software requirements drive hardware replacements more than pure technological innovation. This dynamic has significant implications for companies aiming to manage their IT infrastructure efficiently, cost-effectively, and sustainably.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embodied carbon - the lifecycle of a data center and its carbon footprint</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embodied carbon - the lifecycle of a data center and its carbon footprint" /><published>2025-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-3"><![CDATA[<p>In this third and final edition of our article series on <em>Embodied Carbon</em>, we turn our focus to an often overlooked aspect of digital infrastructure: <strong>the CO₂ emissions of an entire data center over its lifecycle</strong>. While many sustainability efforts concentrate on the <strong>operational phase</strong>, significant emissions arise <strong>already during the construction phase</strong> and through hardware production. You can find the second part of the series on embodied carbon <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-2">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="construction-phase-a-frequently-underestimated-emission-factor"><strong>Construction Phase: A Frequently Underestimated Emission Factor</strong></h2>

<p>The <strong>construction of a data center</strong> is one of the most emission-intensive phases of its lifecycle. Materials such as <strong>steel, concrete, and aluminum</strong> cause high <strong>CO₂ emissions during production and transportation</strong>. The main environmental impacts stem from:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Concrete Production:</strong> Concrete is responsible for <strong>about 8% of global CO₂ emissions</strong>, primarily due to the <strong>energy-intensive cement production process</strong>. <a href="https://essd.copernicus.org/articles/11/1675/2019/">[Andrew, R. M., 2019]</a> The construction of a medium-sized data center can require several thousand tons of concrete, depending on the size and construction method. Since the production of one ton of cement generates an average of 0.6 to 0.9 tons of CO₂, this results in CO₂ emissions of several thousand tons.</li>
  <li><strong>Steel Production:</strong> Producing <strong>one ton of steel emits roughly 1.5 tons of CO₂</strong>. <a href="https://dechema.de/Themen/Studien%2Bund%2BPositionspapiere/2024%2B03%2BH2%2BKompass/_/H2K_IND_Stahl.pdf">[acatech, 2024]</a> Data centers use <strong>large quantities of steel</strong> for both the building structure and <strong>server racks</strong>. For example, there are approximately <strong>266,000 server racks</strong> in German data centers. <a href="https://www.umweltbundesamt.de/sites/default/files/medien/461/publikationen/4037.pdf">[Umweltbundesamt, 2010]</a> The <strong>CO₂ emissions per ton of steel</strong> vary considerably depending on the <strong>production method</strong>. While traditional methods generate high emissions, new technologies such as the <strong>use of green hydrogen</strong> could significantly improve the balance. These approaches, however, are still in the <strong>development phase</strong> and require <strong>high energy input</strong>. <a href="https://dwv-info.de/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/20210616-EP-Gruener-Stahl-min-1.pdf">[DWV, 2021]</a></li>
  <li><strong>Aluminum Processing:</strong> <strong>Aluminum has a high energy density</strong> during production but is widely used in data centers due to its <strong>light weight</strong> and <strong>corrosion resistance</strong>. <strong>Producing one ton of primary aluminum emits on average 11.5 tons of CO₂.</strong> The exact figure may vary depending on the <strong>production method</strong> and <strong>energy source</strong>. Aluminum production is particularly energy-intensive, as the <strong>extraction from bauxite</strong> requires vast amounts of electricity. <a href="https://international-aluminium.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/CF-Good-Guidance-v1-2018.pdf">[International Aluminium Institute, 2018]</a></li>
  <li><strong>Energy Consumption During Construction:</strong> The <strong>construction phase</strong> demands <strong>large quantities of electrical energy</strong> for machinery, transportation, and the assembly of IT infrastructure. Since most <strong>construction equipment runs on fossil fuels</strong>, significant <strong>CO₂ emissions</strong> are generated – especially from <strong>diesel-powered excavators, cranes, and concrete mixers</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="operational-phase-the-main-contributor-to-co-emissions"><strong>Operational Phase: The Main Contributor to CO₂ Emissions</strong></h2>

<p>After completion, the <strong>operation of a data center</strong> continuously generates emissions, primarily due to the <strong>power consumption for IT hardware, cooling, and supporting infrastructure</strong>. The key factors include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Server Power Consumption:</strong> <strong>Data centers worldwide consumed around 360 TWh of electricity in 2022</strong>, which is about <strong>1.7% of the global energy demand</strong>. <a href="https://www.gewinn.com/artikel/rechenzentren-sind-wachstumstreiber-der-stromnachfrage">[Gewinn, 2024]</a>, <a href="https://de.statista.com/statistik/daten/studie/239764/umfrage/weltweiter-stromverbrauch/">[Statista, 2024]</a> The actual <strong>emissions depend heavily on the energy mix</strong> – while <strong>renewable energy sources can minimize the CO₂ footprint</strong>, fossil fuels lead to significant emissions.</li>
  <li><strong>Cooling:</strong> Cooling can account for up to <strong>40% of the total energy consumption</strong>. <a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_IT">[Wikipedia]</a> <strong>Efficient cooling methods</strong>, such as <strong>liquid cooling</strong> or <strong>utilizing outside air</strong>, can considerably reduce emissions.</li>
  <li><strong>Power Usage Effectiveness (PUE):</strong> <strong>Modern data centers achieve PUE values of 1.2 or lower</strong>, whereas <strong>older facilities may exceed values of 2</strong>, leading to massive energy losses. <a href="https://www.computerweekly.com/de/meinung/Energieeffizienz-von-Rechenzentren-aus-alt-mach-nachhaltig">[Computer Weekly, 2023]</a> <strong>The PUE value describes the ratio between the total energy consumption of a data center and the energy actually used for IT infrastructure</strong> – the lower the value, the <strong>more efficiently the energy is used</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>Backup Systems:</strong> <strong>Diesel generators as backup power units generate significant CO₂ emissions</strong> and air pollution, particularly in <strong>older facilities</strong>. <a href="https://www.bund-hessen.de/pm/news/bund-klagt-gegen-zu-hohe-emissionen-aus-notstromdieselmotoren-von-rechenzentren/">[Umweltbundesamt, 2022]</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="decommissioning-and-recycling-what-happens-after-1525-years"><strong>Decommissioning and Recycling: What Happens After 15–25 Years?</strong></h2>

<p>After approximately <strong>15–25 years</strong>, a <strong>data center is either modernized or decommissioned</strong>. This step also causes <strong>environmental impacts</strong>:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Disposal of Building Materials:</strong> Without a <strong>sustainable deconstruction concept</strong>, large amounts of <strong>concrete, steel, and other building materials end up in landfills</strong> rather than being recycled.</li>
  <li><strong>Electronic Waste:</strong> <strong>Over 60 million tons of electronic waste are generated worldwide each year</strong>, of which <strong>only a fraction is recycled</strong>. <a href="https://ewastemonitor.info/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/GEM_2024_EN_11_NOV-web.pdf">[unitar, 2024]</a></li>
</ul>

<p>You can find out more about the environmental problems associated with the extraction of raw materials and the disposal of IT hardware in our previous article. <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-2">Read here</a></p>

<h2 id="environmental-impact-of-data-centers-over-their-entire-lifecycle"><strong>Environmental Impact of Data Centers Over Their Entire Lifecycle</strong></h2>

<p>The <strong>BUND</strong> conducted a study in <strong>2018</strong> to assess the <strong>resource consumption</strong> and <strong>CO₂ emissions</strong> of various data centers over their <strong>entire lifecycle</strong>. <a href="https://www.umweltbundesamt.de/sites/default/files/medien/1410/publikationen/2018-02-23_texte_19-2018_ressourceneffizienz-rechenzentren.pdf">[Bundesumweltamt, 2018]</a> The environmental impacts were divided into <strong>four phases</strong>: <strong>production</strong> (green), distribution, usage, and disposal.**</p>

<p>The model data centers were:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>DC1:</strong> A <strong>municipal data center</strong> with an <strong>IT rated capacity of 750 kW</strong>. It is used for <strong>managed services and colocation</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>DC2:</strong> A <strong>web hosting data center</strong> with an <strong>IT rated capacity of 83 kW</strong>. It primarily provides <strong>hosting services</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>DC3:</strong> An <strong>IT consulting data center</strong> with an <strong>IT rated capacity of 192 kW</strong>. It mainly serves <strong>internal corporate services</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p>The environmental impacts of the data centers were analyzed based on various <strong>indicators</strong>:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>ADP (Abiotic Depletion Potential):</strong> This measures the impact on the availability of <strong>non-renewable resources</strong> such as <strong>metals and fossil fuels</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>KEA (Cumulative Energy Demand):</strong> This indicator describes the <strong>total amount of energy</strong> required over the <strong>lifecycle</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>GHG (Greenhouse Gas Potential):</strong> This indicator measures the <strong>CO₂ emissions</strong> over the entire <strong>lifecycle</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>Water Consumption:</strong> This indicator assesses the <strong>total water usage</strong> throughout the <strong>lifecycle</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/Relative_Umweltauswirkungen_Rechenzentrum.png" alt="Relative distribution of the environmental impacts of data centers by lifecycle phase" />
<small> <a href="https://www.umweltbundesamt.de/sites/default/files/medien/1410/publikationen/2018-02-23_texte_19-2018_ressourceneffizienz-rechenzentren.pdf">Bundesumweltamt, 2018</a></small></p>

<p>The analysis clearly shows that across all indicators, <strong>the operational phase is the largest contributor to environmental impact</strong>, particularly in terms of <strong>energy consumption and CO₂ emissions</strong>. However, the <strong>production of hardware</strong> also contributes <strong>significantly</strong> to the environmental impacts, especially regarding the <strong>abiotic depletion potential</strong>. In contrast, the <strong>disposal phase</strong> has a <strong>comparatively low share</strong> of the overall impacts. Although this study was published back in 2018, its findings remain highly relevant, as the fundamental sources of emissions and environmental impacts of data centers have hardly changed since then.</p>

<h2 id="measures-towards-greener-data-centers"><strong>Measures Towards Greener Data Centers</strong></h2>

<p>To minimize the <strong>environmental impact</strong> of a data center over its <strong>entire lifecycle</strong>, various approaches are necessary:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Sustainable Construction:</strong> Using <strong>CO₂-reduced concrete, recycled steel</strong> and <strong>sustainable materials</strong> can lower emissions during the construction phase.</li>
  <li><strong>Energy-Efficient Hardware:</strong> <strong>Modern processors and memory technologies</strong> with <strong>lower power consumption</strong> reduce the <strong>CO₂ output</strong> during operation.</li>
  <li><strong>Green Energy Sources:</strong> Using <strong>renewable energies</strong> such as <strong>wind and solar power</strong> can make a data center’s electricity consumption nearly <strong>climate-neutral</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>Waste Heat Recovery:</strong> Through <strong>intelligent heat recovery systems</strong>, data centers can channel their waste heat to <strong>local residential or industrial areas</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>Circular Economy:</strong> The <strong>reuse</strong> and <strong>recycling</strong> of <strong>servers, building materials</strong> and other <strong>components</strong> can extend their <strong>lifespan</strong> and <strong>reduce waste</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>

<p><strong>Data centers are the backbone of the digital world, yet they generate significant CO₂ emissions over their entire lifecycle.</strong> While the <strong>ongoing electricity consumption</strong> often takes center stage, the <strong>construction phase</strong> as well as the <strong>disposal of building materials and hardware</strong> must not be neglected.</p>

<p>Through <strong>sustainable construction practices, energy-efficient hardware, renewable energy, waste heat recovery, and a circular economy approach</strong>, companies can significantly reduce their <strong>ecological footprint</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>It is time to design the IT infrastructure of the future so that it is not only high-performing but also sustainable.</strong></p>

<p>For more insights into the topic of embodied carbon, it is worth taking a look at the <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">first</a> and <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-2">second</a> part of the series.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this third and final edition of our article series on Embodied Carbon, we turn our focus to an often overlooked aspect of digital infrastructure: the CO₂ emissions of an entire data center over its lifecycle. While many sustainability efforts concentrate on the operational phase, significant emissions arise already during the construction phase and through hardware production. You can find the second part of the series on embodied carbon here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embodied carbon - environmental impact of hardware production and disposal</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embodied carbon - environmental impact of hardware production and disposal" /><published>2025-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-2"><![CDATA[<p>Whether smartphone, laptop or server - every IT device begins its life cycle with a massive consumption of resources. Even before we switch on a device for the first time, it has already left a considerable ecological footprint. From the extraction of raw materials and energy-intensive manufacturing processes to the growing problem of electronic waste: the invisible environmental costs of IT are enormous. This article sheds light on the darker side of hardware production. We show how the extraction of raw materials, energy-intensive manufacturing processes and e-waste impact the environment. We also present strategies to reduce the ecological footprint of the IT industry. You can find the first part of this article series <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/en/embodied-carbon-1">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="commodity-extraction-an-environmental-and-social-hotspot"><strong>Commodity extraction: an environmental and social hotspot</strong></h2>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/smartphone_resources.jpg" alt="Raw materials that make up a smartphone" />
<small>Quelle: <a href="https://www.regenwald-schuetzen.org/regenwald-wissen/faszination-regenwald/haeufige-fragen/welche-rohstoffe-gibt-es">OroVerde - Die Tropenwaldstiftung</a></small></p>

<p>IT devices consist of a variety of materials such as silicon, copper, gold and rare earths. However, their extraction has serious consequences for people and the environment:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Habitat Destruction:</b> The extraction of gold, lithium, and cobalt leads to deforestation of rainforests, soil contamination, and loss of natural habitats. Cobalt mining in the Democratic Republic of the Congo has already destroyed over <b>500,000 hectares of rainforest</b> (Source: Global Forest Watch, 2023).</li>
<li><b>Soil contamination:</b> Many mining processes release toxic chemicals that can contaminate the soil. Particularly problematic is gold extraction using cyanide leaching, where toxic residues are often disposed of improperly, causing extensive soil contamination (<a href="https://earthworks.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Earthworks-Annual-Report-2023.pdf">[Source: Earthworks, 2023]</a>). Another critical issue is the release of toxic heavy metals from ore mining and refining processes, which can pollute the soil in the long term (<a href="https://earthworks.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Earthworks-Annual-Report-2023.pdf">[Source: Earthworks, 2023]</a>).</li>
<li><b>Water Consumption and Pollution:</b> Lithium extraction in the Atacama Desert consumes up to <b>2 million liters of water per ton of lithium</b> <a href="https://www.fr.de/wirtschaft/konflikte-wasser-10968084.html">[Source: Friends of the Earth, 2022]</a>. This leads to the drying out of local ecosystems and endangers indigenous communities.</li>
<li><b>Social Issues:</b> Up to <b>40,000 children work in cobalt mines</b> in the Democratic Republic of the Congo under hazardous conditions <a href="https://www.amnesty.de/informieren/aktuell/demokratische-republik-kongo-grosskonzerne-tun-zu-wenig-gegen-kinderarbeit">[Source: Amnesty International, 2023]</a>. Additionally, profits from raw materials finance armed conflicts and destabilize entire regions.</li>
</ul>

<p>According to the International Energy Agency (IEA), demand for these raw materials will more than double by <strong>2040</strong>, which will further exacerbate the negative consequences. <a href="https://www.iea.org/news/sharp-declines-in-critical-mineral-prices-mask-risks-of-future-supply-strains-as-energy-transitions-advance">Source: International Energy Agency, 2024</a></p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/Smartphone_resources_map.jpg" alt="Map - Where which raw materials are mined" />
<small>Quelle: <a href="https://everphone.com/de/blog/oekologische-handys/">everphone</a></small></p>

<h2 id="energy-intensive-production-the-hidden-co-driver"><strong>Energy-intensive production: the hidden CO₂ driver</strong></h2>

<p>The extraction of raw materials is followed by an energy-intensive manufacturing process that causes enormous amounts of CO₂ emissions:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Semiconductor Manufacturing:</b> Producing microchips demands extremely high levels of purity, involving significant water and chemical consumption. Particularly problematic is production in Taiwan, which accounts for over <b>90% of global high-end chip manufacturing</b> <a href="https://www.economist.com/special-report/2023/03/06/taiwans-dominance-of-the-chip-industry-makes-it-more-important">[Source: The Economist, 2023]</a>. Manufacturing a single 30 cm silicon wafer consumes <b>up to 8,000 liters of water</b>—an enormous strain for water-scarce regions like Taiwan. <a href="https://www.globalwaterintel.com">[Source: Global Water Intelligence (2009) Pure Water, Semiconductors and The Recession]</a></li>
<li><b>Circuit Board Manufacturing:</b> Etching copper traces produces toxic chemicals, which are often improperly disposed of. In China, where a large share of global circuit board production occurs, <b>thousands of tons of heavy metals and acids</b> contaminate the environment each year, polluting agricultural land and water sources. <a href="https://www.fraunhofer-zukunftsfabrik.de/?p=4256">[Source: Fraunhofer Institute, 2023]</a> Some manufacturers are now adopting alternative processes that reduce chemical use, but widespread implementation remains limited.</li>
<li><b>Battery production:</b> The production of lithium-ion batteries is among the most energy-intensive processes in the IT industry. Electrode manufacturing and cell assembly, in particular, require high temperatures and cleanroom conditions, leading to enormous energy consumption. Studies indicate that producing a lithium battery generates between <b>61</b> and <b>106 kg CO₂-equivalents per kWh battery capacity</b> <a href="https://ivl.diva-portal.org/smash/get/diva2:1549551/FULLTEXT01.pdf">[Source: IVL Swedish Environmental Research Institute, 2019]</a>. In addition to the high electricity usage, substantial amounts of waste, including toxic solvents and electrolyte residues, are produced. Although manufacturers are exploring innovative alternatives like solid-state batteries and more efficient recycling methods, in the short term, battery production remains environmentally challenging.</li>
</ul>

<p>Transportation routes: an often overlooked factor</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/smartphone_supply_chain.png" alt="Production cuts in smartphone manufacturing" />
<small>Quelle: <a href="https://www.bild.de/bild-plus/digital/smartphone-und-tablet/smartphone/langer-weg-eines-handys-53442300.bild.html">Bild</a></small></p>

<ul>
<li><b>Shipping:</b> Container ships, which also transport IT components across the world's oceans, emitted <b>932 million tons of CO₂</b> in 2015. <a href="https://www.umweltbundesamt.de/themen/wasser/gewaesser/meere/nutzung-belastungen/schifffahrt#fakten-zur-seeschifffahrt-und-zu-ihren-auswirkungen-auf-die-umwelt">[Source: German Environment Agency (Umweltbundesamt), 2023]</a></li>
<li><b>Air Freight:</b> Particularly fast deliveries via aircraft are even more harmful to the climate—air transport generates about <b>180 times more CO₂ emissions per ton of freight than sea transport</b>. <a href="https://www.itf-oecd.org/sites/default/files/docs/dp201421.pdf">[Source: International Transport Forum, 2014]</a></li>
<li><b>Last Mile:</b> Delivery to end customers by truck or courier also contributes significantly to the CO₂ footprint, especially due to the growth in online retail.</li>
</ul>

<p>Measures such as shortening supply chains, using more energy-efficient means of transportation and regional production sites could significantly reduce these emissions.</p>

<h2 id="electrical-waste-the-unsolved-disposal-problem"><strong>Electrical waste: the unsolved disposal problem</strong></h2>

<p>Every year, over <strong>50 million tons of electronic waste</strong> are generated worldwide - less than 20% is recycled. IT devices contain valuable raw materials such as gold, copper and cobalt, but also hazardous substances that need to be disposed of in an environmentally friendly manner:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Gold, Copper, and Cobalt:</b> Recycling can recover these materials for use in new products. For example, recycled gold is already being reused in smartphones, reducing the demand for newly mined gold. <a href="https://globalewastemonitor.org/">[Source: Global e-Waste Monitor, 2022]</a></li>
<li><b>Toxic Substances:</b> Many devices contain lead, mercury, and flame retardants, posing risks to both the environment and human health. Improperly disposed devices can leak these substances into groundwater, causing long-term damage to ecosystems. <a href="https://wedocs.unep.org/xmlui/bitstream/handle/20.500.11822/35364/CoCL.pdf">[Source: UNEP, 2020]</a></li>
<li><b>Illegal Waste Disposal:</b> Old IT hardware is frequently exported to developing countries, where it is dismantled under hazardous conditions. According to research by the Basel Action Network (BAN), approximately <b>352,474 tons of electronic waste are illegally exported from Europe annually</b>, often disguised as recycling. In countries such as Ghana, massive e-waste dumps have emerged, where workers inhale toxic fumes without protective equipment, exposing them to severe health risks. <a href="https://wiki.ban.org/images/f/f4/Holes_in_the_Circular_Economy-_WEEE_Leakage_from_Europe.pdf">[Source: Basel Action Network, 2019]</a></li>
</ul>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/elektroschrott_recycling.jpeg" alt="Electronic waste by continent" />
<small>Source: <a href="https://de.statista.com/infografik/33250/elektroabfaelle-nach-regionen/">Statista</a></small></p>

<h2 id="refurbished-hardware-and-the-circular-economy-keeping-resources-in-circulation"><strong>Refurbished hardware and the circular economy: keeping resources in circulation</strong></h2>

<p>One of the most effective measures for more sustainable IT is <strong>extending the lifespan of devices</strong>. Instead of replacing hardware after a few years, companies and consumers can rely on <strong>refurbished devices</strong> - professionally refurbished devices that are technically modernized and reused. This alternative not only reduces costs, but also the enormous <strong>resource consumption of new productions</strong>. In addition, the use of refurbished hardware can reduce <strong>CO₂ emissions, resource consumption and electronic waste by up to 80%</strong> compared to new devices. <a href="https://www.refurbed.de/a/pressrelease-refurbed-fraunhofer/">[Source: refurbed, 2024]</a> In addition to economic benefits, extending the service life of devices also helps to reduce e-waste, as fewer old devices need to be disposed of. Companies that rely on refurbished hardware not only benefit from lower acquisition costs, but also from positive sustainability effects that are reflected in their ESG balance sheet.</p>

<p>The circular economy** approach is even more consistent. The aim here is to keep <strong>IT devices, their components and materials in the usage cycle for as long as possible</strong> instead of disposing of them after a short time. Manufacturers must increasingly focus on <strong>modular, repairable designs</strong> and facilitate access to <strong>spare parts</strong>. Many components that are considered “obsolete” in the traditional IT value chain can still provide valuable services in other areas. One example: <strong>Servers</strong> decommissioned in data centers often find a second use as inexpensive, powerful machines in smaller companies. <a href="https://www.ellenmacarthurfoundation.org/circular-economy-diagram">[Source: Ellen MacArthur Foundation, 2023]</a></p>

<p>In addition, <strong>recycling can recover valuable raw materials such as gold, copper and rare earths</strong>, reducing the environmental impact of new extraction. <strong>Tech giants like Apple are already using recycled aluminum</strong> in their MacBooks, while Google aims to use only recycled materials in all of its hardware products by 2030 <a href="https://www.apple.com/environment/pdf/Apple_Environmental_Progress_Report_2024.pdf">[Source: Apple Environmental Progress Report, 2023]</a>; <a href="https://sustainability.google/reports/google-2023-environmental-report/">[Google Sustainability Report, 2023]</a>. However, <strong>consumers are also called upon</strong> to exploit the full impact of the circular economy: Those who consciously opt for <strong>long-lasting, repairable or refurbished devices</strong> actively contribute to the <strong>reduction of electronic waste and CO₂ emissions</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="ways-to-a-more-sustainable-it"><strong>Ways to a more sustainable IT</strong></h2>

<p>Sustainability in IT requires a rethink along the entire life cycle of hardware and software. <strong>Longer usage times, targeted recycling and a consistent circular economy</strong> are key levers for conserving resources and reducing emissions. Companies and consumers alike can take responsibility - be it by purchasing long-lasting hardware, using refurbished devices or consciously handling electronic waste.</p>

<p>The next article is about the <strong>lifecycle of a data center</strong>. We show what environmental impacts arise from construction to dismantling and which sustainable strategies help to minimize the carbon footprint. Click <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-3">here</a> for the third part of the series. You can find an overview of embodied carbon <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1">here</a> in the first part of the series.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina, Marcel</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Whether smartphone, laptop or server - every IT device begins its life cycle with a massive consumption of resources. Even before we switch on a device for the first time, it has already left a considerable ecological footprint. From the extraction of raw materials and energy-intensive manufacturing processes to the growing problem of electronic waste: the invisible environmental costs of IT are enormous. This article sheds light on the darker side of hardware production. We show how the extraction of raw materials, energy-intensive manufacturing processes and e-waste impact the environment. We also present strategies to reduce the ecological footprint of the IT industry. You can find the first part of this article series here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embodied carbon in IT - the hidden carbon footprint of our digital world</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embodied carbon in IT - the hidden carbon footprint of our digital world" /><published>2025-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-1"><![CDATA[<p>In today’s digital world, much revolves around software, data, and networking. However, behind every digital application lies a physical infrastructure: data centers, servers, networking technology, and end devices. While the focus is often on energy efficiency and renewable power sources, a significant environmental impact remains overlooked – <em>Embodied Carbon</em>.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-embodied-carbon"><strong>What is Embodied Carbon?</strong></h2>

<p>The term <em>Embodied Carbon</em> refers to the total CO₂ emissions generated throughout the lifecycle of an IT product – from raw material extraction to production, transportation, and disposal. Unlike <em>Operational Carbon</em>, which accounts for emissions from energy consumption during use, <em>Embodied Carbon</em> often constitutes the larger share of environmental impact.</p>

<p>For example: <strong>Up to 98% of the total CO₂ emissions of a smartphone or laptop occur during manufacturing.</strong> Similarly, the production of a server, depending on its configuration, <strong>generates between 100 and 3,000 kilograms of CO₂ equivalents.</strong> The <strong>Embodied Carbon</strong> accounts for approximately <strong>75% of the total CO₂ emissions of a rack server.</strong> In comparison: <strong>A smartphone generates around 55 kilograms of CO₂ equivalents due to Embodied Carbon, while a laptop generates about 300 kilograms.</strong> <a href="https://globalelectronicscouncil.org/wp-content/uploads/GEC_Climate_Change_SOSR_DRAFT_For_Public_Comment_1APR2021.pdf">(Source)</a></p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/smart-phone_vs_rack-server-de.png" alt="Comparison of Embodied Carbon and Operational Carbon in IT hardware" />
<small>Source: <a href="https://globalelectronicscouncil.org/wp-content/uploads/GEC_Climate_Change_SOSR_DRAFT_For_Public_Comment_1APR2021.pdf">globalelectronicscouncil.org</a></small></p>

<p><img class="img-fluid w-100" src="/assets/images/blog/carbon-compairison-different-devices-de.png" alt="Comparison of Embodied Carbon and Operational Carbon in IT hardware" />
<small>Source: <a href="https://globalelectronicscouncil.org/wp-content/uploads/GEC_Climate_Change_SOSR_DRAFT_For_Public_Comment_1APR2021.pdf">globalelectronicscouncil.org</a></small></p>

<h2 id="why-is-embodied-carbon-so-relevant"><strong>Why is Embodied Carbon So Relevant?</strong></h2>

<p>The production of IT hardware is extremely resource- and energy-intensive. It requires the extraction and processing of rare materials such as cobalt, lithium, silicon, and gold. The environmental consequences are severe:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>High energy consumption</b>: The production of microprocessors and other high-tech components requires vast amounts of electricity, often sourced from fossil fuels.</li>
<li><b>Resource exploitation</b>: The extraction of rare metals leads to environmental destruction, water pollution, and social issues in mining regions.</li>
<li><b>Short life cycles</b>: Rapidly changing technology trends result in shorter device lifespans – often replaced despite still being functional.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="ways-to-reduce-embodied-carbon"><strong>Ways to Reduce Embodied Carbon</strong></h2>

<p>To mitigate the <em>Embodied Carbon</em> of IT hardware, several strategies are essential:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Extended device lifespan</b>: Repairs, upgrades, and prolonged usage of devices significantly improve their environmental balance.</li>
<li><b>Circular economy</b>: Companies should focus on reuse and recycling to recover raw materials and reduce the need for new production.</li>
<li><b>Sustainable manufacturing</b>: Manufacturers must develop lower-emission production processes and increase the use of recycled materials.</li>
<li><b>Conscious consumer behavior</b>: Users can contribute by making informed purchasing decisions and adopting sustainable IT strategies.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>

<p>While the IT industry has made great strides in reducing <em>Operational Carbon</em>, <em>Embodied Carbon</em> remains an often-overlooked factor. Businesses and consumers must recognize the full environmental impact and implement sustainable strategies to minimize CO₂ emissions throughout a product’s lifecycle.</p>

<p><strong>Sustainable IT does not begin when a device is powered on – it starts with its production.</strong></p>

<h2 id="outlook"><strong>Outlook</strong></h2>

<p>In the upcoming articles in this series, we will take a closer look at the environmental impact of hardware production and disposal. We will also look at the life cycle of data centers and analyze their environmental challenges and possible sustainable solutions. <a href="https://mehrwert.tech/embodied-carbon-2">Click here</a> for the second part of the series.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina, Marcel</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In today’s digital world, much revolves around software, data, and networking. However, behind every digital application lies a physical infrastructure: data centers, servers, networking technology, and end devices. While the focus is often on energy efficiency and renewable power sources, a significant environmental impact remains overlooked – Embodied Carbon.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green software, green future - sustainability in the digital age</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-software" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green software, green future - sustainability in the digital age" /><published>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-software</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-software"><![CDATA[<p>Whether uploading a photo, streaming a movie or using a cloud app - the internet makes our everyday lives more convenient. But this convenience comes at a price: enormous energy consumption that often remains invisible. Every digital action - from sending an email to using data-intensive AI services - adds up to a global energy consumption comparable to that of the global aviation industry.</p>

<p>At a time when the climate crisis and sustainability are key issues, the IT industry is also coming under the spotlight. How can we make the digital world more efficient and environmentally friendly? And what role does green coding play in this?</p>

<h4 id="the-internets-hunger-for-energy">The internet’s hunger for energy</h4>
<p>At first glance, the internet appears to be an invisible global network, but behind it lies an impressive physical infrastructure. Whether writing emails, streaming videos or making search queries - everything we do online passes through global networks and ultimately ends up in data centers. These “hubs” of the internet are indispensable for the digital world, but they consume enormous amounts of energy.</p>

<p>According to the International Energy Agency (IEA), data centers will consume around 200 terawatt hours of electricity worldwide in 2022, which corresponds to just under 1% of global electricity consumption. By comparison, this is almost equivalent to the annual energy requirements of countries such as Thailand. This consumption will continue to rise as global data traffic increases by around 20-30% annually.</p>

<p>Data-intensive applications such as streaming services or AI applications in particular are contributing massively to this. Here are a few examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>Streaming a two-hour 4K movie requires around 15 kWh of energy - enough to keep a light bulb on for 150 hours.</li>
<li>Uploading a 10 MB photo consumes around 0.2 kWh - equivalent to the power consumption of an LED lamp for around 12 hours.</li>
<li>One hour of using a cloud service to process large files can consume up to 0.5 kWh, which corresponds to the power consumption of an average lamp for approx. 25 hours.</li></ul>

<h4 id="the-connection-between-it-and-power-consumption">The connection between IT and power consumption</h4>
<p>The increasing energy requirements of IT infrastructure have far-reaching effects on global electricity consumption and therefore on our environment. High energy consumption leads to increased CO₂ emissions, especially in regions that generate most of their electricity from fossil fuels.</p>

<p>Global electricity consumption amounted to around 28,000 terawatt hours (TWh) in 2023. IT and digital technologies account for a significant proportion of this. It is particularly problematic that many data centers are still powered by coal, gas or oil-fired power plants, which leads to high CO₂ emissions. It is estimated that the IT industry is already responsible for 2-4% of global CO₂ emissions - a proportion that is comparable to the aviation industry and is continuing to rise.</p>

<p>The climate targets make the urgency clear: global greenhouse gas emissions are to be drastically reduced by 2050 in order to limit global warming to a maximum of 1.5 °C. However, in view of the growing energy consumption due to digital technologies and developments to date, this target no longer seems achievable. This makes it all the more important to systematically restructure the economy and the technology sector in particular in order to curb climate change as much as possible.</p>

<p>This is where green IT comes in: more efficient technologies, the switch to renewable energies and resource-saving approaches such as green coding are no longer visions of the future, but urgently needed solutions.</p>

<h4 id="resource-consumption-beyond-energy">Resource consumption beyond energy</h4>
<p>In addition to energy consumption, the consumption of resources in IT is also of crucial importance. The manufacture and disposal of devices such as servers, computers and mobile devices requires a large number of raw materials, including rare earths. These raw materials are only available in very limited quantities and their extraction and processing in particular entail considerable risks for the environment. The disposal of electronic waste is also a growing problem, as many devices are not recycled or reused. A sustainable IT industry must therefore not only reduce energy consumption, but also optimize the use of resources and extend the service life of devices.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding---code-neu-denken">Green Coding - Code neu denken</h4>
<p>Green Coding takes a holistic approach to minimizing the energy consumption of software and digital applications. The aim is to design digital products in such a way that they conserve resources while maximizing their functionality. Three principles play a decisive role here:</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Energy Efficiency:</b> Software should be optimized so that its operation consumes less energy. This means, for example, that computing operations are carried out more efficiently and resource-intensive processes are minimized.</li>
<li><b>Hardware Efficiency:</b> The software must work efficiently with the hardware in order to reduce energy consumption. This also includes optimizing software so that it harmonizes better with existing devices and infrastructures. The aim is to achieve the longest possible hardware life cycle.</li>
<li><b>Carbon Awareness:</b> Developers should be aware of the CO₂ emissions generated by the operation of software and its infrastructure. The aim is to design digital products and applications in such a way that they have a minimal carbon footprint.</li></ul>

<h4 id="shaping-a-sustainable-digital-future">Shaping a sustainable digital future</h4>
<p>The energy consumption of the internet and IT infrastructure is a significant factor in the global energy budget. Data centers contribute significantly to this consumption. However, it is possible to significantly reduce the impact through green IT and especially green coding. Here are a few examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Use of green energy:</b> Many data centers are increasingly turning to renewable energies to make their operations more climate-friendly. Switching to solar, wind or hydroelectric power can significantly reduce CO₂ emissions. Large companies such as Google and Microsoft have already started to run their data centers on 100% renewable energy and are even aiming to make their entire infrastructure CO₂-neutral.</li>
<li><b>Recycling of waste heat:</b> Some data centers use the waste heat generated to heat neighbouring buildings or even feed it into district heating networks. One example of this is the EcoDataCenter data center in Sweden, which uses its waste heat to supply a nearby residential area with energy. Such innovative approaches not only help to optimize energy consumption, but also contribute to reducing CO₂ emissions.</li></ul>

<p>The digital transformation offers many opportunities, but it also brings with it the responsibility to make our technologies as efficient and resource-saving as possible. Green coding is a crucial part of this responsibility, as it aims to operate the digital world with less energy and therefore fewer CO₂ emissions. To this end, the companies that develop and operate these technologies must also be held accountable by ensuring that their infrastructure - from software to data centers - is as green and sustainable as possible.</p>

<p>Overall, as a society and as an industry, we need to recognize that the transition to more sustainable IT practices is not just an option, but an urgent obligation. It is up to us to shape the digital future in a way that promotes both technological progress and the protection of our planet.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Whether uploading a photo, streaming a movie or using a cloud app - the internet makes our everyday lives more convenient. But this convenience comes at a price: enormous energy consumption that often remains invisible. Every digital action - from sending an email to using data-intensive AI services - adds up to a global energy consumption comparable to that of the global aviation industry.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green coding - sustainability in software development</title><link href="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green coding - sustainability in software development" /><published>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mehrwert.tech/green-coding"><![CDATA[<p>At a time when the climate crisis and sustainability have become key issues, the IT industry and its energy consumption are also coming more into focus. The constant increase in energy requirements and the growing consumption of resources are presenting companies and developers with new challenges. In this context, green coding approaches are becoming increasingly relevant. It offers solutions to make software more efficient and thus make a direct contribution to reducing its ecological footprint.</p>

<h4 id="what-is-behind-green-coding"><strong>What is behind green coding?</strong></h4>
<p>Green coding is a comprehensive approach that optimizes not only the code itself, but also the entire software architecture. It takes into account the consumption of resources over the entire life cycle of the software in order to keep this as low as possible. Decisions such as the choice of algorithms, data structuring and the location of the data center play an important role. For example, the use of scalable system architectures can reduce energy consumption and ensure that software runs more efficiently on different hardware configurations. The selection of energy-efficient programming languages, such as Rust, also makes a significant contribution to reducing power consumption.</p>

<h4 id="benefits-for-companies-and-the-environment"><strong>Benefits for companies and the environment</strong></h4>
<p>Companies that implement green coding practices benefit from numerous advantages. These not only have a positive impact on the environment, but also increase the company’s competitiveness.By reducing energy consumption, operating costs are reduced and the service life of the hardware can also be extended. Furthermore, companies that invest in sustainable software development make an active contribution to their ESG criteria (Environmental, Social, Governance), which are increasingly expected by investors and the public. With the introduction of the Corporate Sustainability Reporting Directive (CSRD) in the EU, many companies are now obliged to report regularly on their sustainability practices.The integration of green coding not only supports the fulfillment of these reporting obligations, but also strengthens the corporate image in terms of environmental responsibility.</p>

<h4 id="approaches-for-companies"><strong>Approaches for companies</strong></h4>
<p>One promising option for companies to implement green coding is the use of cloud infrastructures and virtualization technologies. These not only offer the flexibility to scale resources as required, but also the opportunity to use them more efficiently. If companies choose cloud service providers that operate their data centers with renewable energy, they can further reduce their CO2 emissions. At the same time, it is important to continuously monitor energy consumption in order to identify and exploit potential savings at an early stage. After all, we can only improve what we measure. As energy consumption cannot always be measured directly, companies should use proxy values to estimate consumption in such cases.</p>

<h4 id="challenges-and-opportunities"><strong>Challenges and opportunities</strong></h4>
<p>Rebound effects often occur when savings in one area are offset by increased use in another area. For example, more efficient software could lead to it being used more frequently, which would result in higher energy consumption overall. To prevent such effects, it is crucial to understand sustainability as a long-term strategy. By continuously improving the software and taking environmental effects into account throughout the entire development phase, a permanent reduction in resource consumption can be achieved.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding-as-a-corporate-strategy"><strong>Green coding as a corporate strategy</strong></h4>
<p>Green coding is not only a means of reducing CO2 emissions, but also a driver of innovation. Companies that focus on sustainable software development are positioning themselves as pioneers in the field of green technologies - one of the fastest growing markets in Germany. This not only gives them a competitive advantage, but also makes an important contribution to the digital transformation by developing technologies that meet the requirements of a sustainable future.</p>

<p>However, sustainable software development involves more than just efficient code or innovative technologies. It also requires a holistic view of the energy and resource requirements of digital services.</p>

<h4 id="the-energy-requirements-of-digital-services"><strong>The energy requirements of digital services</strong></h4>
<p>The high energy consumption of digital services makes it urgently necessary to evaluate them not only in terms of their functionality, but also with regard to their ecological footprint. The choice of data center in which applications are operated has a major influence on energy efficiency. Data centers that are powered by renewable energy or are located in regions where energy requirements are predominantly covered by sustainable sources can significantly reduce CO2 emissions. In addition, waste heat from data centers can be reused, for example through district heating or to heat greenhouses. Technologies such as edge computing also help to bring computing power closer to the end user and minimize the energy required for data transfer.</p>

<p>However, energy efficiency does not only depend on the infrastructure. The way in which software is developed and designed also plays a decisive role.</p>

<h4 id="more-than-just-optimized-code-the-holistic-approach"><strong>More than just optimized code: The holistic approach</strong></h4>
<p>The architecture of software has a significant influence on its long-term energy efficiency. A modular and scalable architecture makes it possible to flexibly adapt the software to different requirements without wasting unnecessary resources. Another important factor is the use of microservices, which enable applications to be scaled according to demand, thus avoiding unnecessary loads and improving energy efficiency. This approach is particularly advantageous in cloud environments, where resources can be flexibly allocated and released again, leading to a significant reduction in energy consumption.</p>

<p>Modern development practices and close collaboration within the teams are essential for the successful implementation of these approaches.</p>

<h4 id="devops-as-the-key-to-sustainable-software"><strong>DevOps as the key to sustainable software</strong></h4>
<p>DevOps principles promote close collaboration between the development department and IT operations and make it possible to integrate sustainability goals throughout the software lifecycle. Automated testing, continuous delivery and monitoring tools are not only valuable instruments for improving software quality, but also for optimizing resource consumption. By identifying inefficient code passages at an early stage and continuously adapting them to the latest, energy-efficient best practices, more sustainable development is promoted. DevOps also makes it possible to regularly review the energy consumption of software so that developers can take targeted measures to reduce CO2 emissions.</p>

<p>An equally important aspect of sustainable software development is the targeted selection of tools and technologies used in the development process - including the programming language.</p>

<h4 id="programming-language-as-an-influencing-factor"><strong>Programming language as an influencing factor</strong></h4>

<p>The choice of programming language has a significant impact on resource consumption. While interpreted languages such as Python and Ruby are widely used due to their flexibility and ease of use, they often perform worse in terms of efficiency and speed than compiled languages such as Rust or C++. These programming languages work closer to the hardware and offer better memory management and lower energy consumption. A conscious choice of programming language can therefore significantly reduce the ecological footprint of an application and increase performance at the same time.</p>

<p>However, the implementation of green coding goes beyond the choice of programming language. It requires a holistic approach and the implementation of sustainable practices, which are now also being successfully applied by leading companies.</p>

<h4 id="examples-from-practice"><strong>Examples from practice</strong></h4>
<p>Companies such as Google, Apple and Microsoft are not only pioneers in the use of green technologies, but also in the integration of green coding as an integral part of their software development. Google uses AI algorithms to optimize energy consumption in its data centers, Apple is pursuing carbon-neutral production and Microsoft has set itself the goal of becoming CO2-negative by 2030. These best practices serve as role models for other companies that are also striving for more sustainable software development. It is becoming clear that green coding is not only seen as an ethical responsibility, but also as an economic necessity to remain competitive and meet the demands of an increasingly environmentally conscious society.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding-in-germany"><strong>Green Coding in Germany</strong></h4>
<p>In Germany, more and more companies and start-ups are recognizing the importance of green coding and integrating sustainable development practices into their business models. Politicians are also promoting sustainable software development, for example through initiatives such as the ‘Blue Angel’, which tests software products in terms of their energy consumption and resource efficiency. Nevertheless, there is still a lot of potential for improvement, particularly in the area of certifying sustainable software products and establishing uniform standards. Although the path to more sustainable software development is not yet fully paved, current developments show that a change in awareness is underway.</p>

<h4 id="shaping-a-sustainable-digital-future"><strong>Shaping a sustainable digital future</strong></h4>
<p>The responsibility for a sustainable digital future lies not only with developers and companies, but also with consumers, regulatory authorities and society as a whole. Every player in the digital ecosystem must be involved in the transformation process to ensure the sustainable and resource-efficient use of software. Companies that integrate green coding into their processes not only set an example of ecological responsibility, but also prove that economic success and environmental awareness can go hand in hand. At the same time, it is necessary for politicians to create clear framework conditions that pave the way for a sustainable digital transformation, for example through legal requirements for energy efficiency and the promotion of green innovations.</p>

<h4 id="green-coding-as-a-corporate-strategy-1"><strong>Green coding as a corporate strategy</strong></h4>
<p>The integration of green coding into the corporate strategy goes beyond the mere implementation of efficient practices - it is a long-term process that must be deeply rooted in the corporate culture. Companies that successfully implement green coding ensure that sustainability is not just a one-off project, but an ongoing, dynamic challenge. Through close collaboration between development teams, sustainability departments and executives, the potential of green coding is fully exploited to develop sustainable software solutions that minimize the environmental footprint while promoting economic growth.</p>

<h4 id="outlook---the-path-to-a-sustainable-digital-future"><strong>Outlook - The path to a sustainable digital future</strong></h4>
<p>The path to a sustainable digital future requires a comprehensive change in the way software is developed, deployed and used. Green coding plays a key role in this, but in order to achieve the desired climate targets, all players - from software developers to companies and users - must take responsibility. Sustainability in software development is no longer just an option, but a necessity to ensure a future worth living for generations to come. Today’s measures, even if they may seem small, form the basis for a sustainable digital future that is not only technologically advanced but also ecologically responsible.</p>

<p>We want to be an active part of this green digital future and have already made a contribution to bringing sustainable software development into focus. Through our involvement in various publications, we are committed to further raising awareness of green coding and promoting best practices in the industry. Those interested can take a look at the article on Dev Insider, which deals with the importance of green coding and sustainable software development (read here: <a href="https://www.dev-insider.de/green-coding-nachhaltige-softwareentwicklung-a-a6b6dd926903508b9302fe1b2c7f5b0d/" target="_blank">Culturally anchoring green coding in the company</a>). We also contributed to a guideline published by the German Economic Institute, which examines the potential of green coding in the context of digital transformation and provides important impetus for companies and political decision-makers (read more here: &lt;a href=“https://www.wirtschaft-digital-bw.de/fileadmin/media/Dokumente/Studien/20240607_IW4Null_GreenCoding.pdf” target=“_blank”&gt;Green Coding - Increasing efficiency through the intelligent use of software&lt;/a&gt;).</p>]]></content><author><name>Alina, Marcel</name></author><category term="posts" /><category term="#green-coding," /><category term="#nachhaltigkeit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At a time when the climate crisis and sustainability have become key issues, the IT industry and its energy consumption are also coming more into focus. The constant increase in energy requirements and the growing consumption of resources are presenting companies and developers with new challenges. In this context, green coding approaches are becoming increasingly relevant. It offers solutions to make software more efficient and thus make a direct contribution to reducing its ecological footprint.]]></summary></entry></feed>